<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An A.B.C. or holy alphabet conteyning some plaine lessons gathered out of the word, to the number of the letters in the English alphabet, to enter young beginners in the schoole of Christ.</title>
            <author>E. C., fl. 1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 71 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17444</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4264.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114411</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849636</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849636</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14796</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17444)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14796)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1267:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An A.B.C. or holy alphabet conteyning some plaine lessons gathered out of the word, to the number of the letters in the English alphabet, to enter young beginners in the schoole of Christ.</title>
                  <author>E. C., fl. 1626.</author>
                  <author>Cancellar, James, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 125, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I N[orton] for William Shefford, and are to be sold at his shop in Popes head alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1626.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Epistle to the reader signed: E.C.</note>
                  <note>Sometimes wrongly attributed to James Cancellar.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 4563.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 4563 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Biblical teaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14796:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14796:1"/>
            <p>AN A. B. C. OR Holy Alphabet, <hi>Conteyning</hi> Some plaine Leſſons gathered out of the <hi>Word,</hi> to the number of the Letters in the Engliſh Alpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet, to enter Young beginners in the Schoole of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 COR. 3.2.</hi>
               </bibl> I haue fedde you with Milke, and not with Meate, for hitherto ye were not able to beare it; neither yet now are yee able.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>HEBR. 5.12.</hi>
               </bibl> For when for the time yee ought to bee Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers; yet haue ye neede againe, that one teach you what be the firſt principles of the Oracles of God; and are become ſuch as haue need of milke, and not of ſtrong meate.</q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>I N.</hi> for <hi>William Shefford,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Popes head alley,</hi> 1626</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:14796:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14796:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Authors</hi> Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Roſſe IGNO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RANCE, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with ſupine NEGLI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GENCE, in purſuite of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>Knowledge,</hi> I haue, not without griefe, obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, by experience now of twenty yeares exerciſe of my <hi>Miniſtrie,</hi> ſtill to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine,
<pb facs="tcp:14796:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> &amp; euen raigne both in the <hi>Country</hi> and <hi>Citie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This hath made me wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in deſire to become <hi>all to all,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.22</note> and with an ayme of doing good, chiefly to them of mine owne <hi>Country charge,</hi> and <hi>younger people</hi> eſpecially, (in whom my <hi>Miniſtry</hi> through <hi>Gods mercy</hi> hath euer moſt reioyced) to collect this <hi>A. B. C.</hi> or <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phabet</hi> (as I haue thought meete to terme it, the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Elementa prima. Heb. <hi>5.12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles phraſe,</hi> ſounding to ſuch a title) to initiate young be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginners in the moſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie grounds of godlineſſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14796:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Which labour (howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ſome perhaps may ſleight it, as too vulgar, or meane a proiect, or deeme not ſo neceſſary) may I truſt yeeld direction and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement by Gods bleſſing to ſome of his weaker ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants; the matter hereof being, for the moſt part, onely plaine places, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected ſentences, ſeruing pregnantly for ſpeciall pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, of holy Scripture, wherein Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">In eis quae apertè in ſcriptura poſita ſunt, continen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur illa om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia quae co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem moreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que viuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di. <hi>De doct. Chriſt.</hi> lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> hath auouched to bee <hi>contayned all things,</hi> concerning <hi>faith and manners;</hi> and no <hi>weapon</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:14796:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> being like to this<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ</hi> 6.17</note> 
               <hi>ſword of the ſpirit,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">2 <hi>Co.</hi> 10 4</note> 
               <hi>mighty through God to caſt downe holdes,</hi> and to<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12</note> 
               <hi>cut off</hi> ſinne from the very ſoule: Nor any<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.109.</note> 
               <hi>Lamp</hi> or <hi>Torch</hi> for conueying hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly <hi>light,</hi> to be compared with this, which goeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thoſe glorious titles, <hi>of</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 19.7.</note> 
               <hi>the perfect law of the Lord, conuerting the ſoule,</hi> and <hi>ſure teſtimony, making wiſe the ſimple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Onely this I muſt adde, (that the promiſe ſeeme not more then the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance) how it is not in the purpoſe or compaſſe of this
<pb facs="tcp:14796:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Alphabet,</hi> to meddle much with matters of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> already eſtabliſhed in our Chriſtian Church, nor yet to touch vpon all particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of <hi>Chriſtian Practiſe:</hi> neither ſhall I ſeeke to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt theſe directions into any <hi>artificiall frame</hi> or <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod,</hi> as others haue profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably endeauoured in their exact Treatiſes, therein more accommodated to learned and iudicious Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
            <p>All here aymed at is, (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to the <hi>prefixed title</hi>) to deliuer ſome <hi>rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:14796:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> that may yeeld <hi>inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> to poore <hi>ignorant</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (of whom the world is yet full, for all our learned and elaborate preaching) and ſet forward <hi>young be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginners,</hi> not capable for their weakeneſſe of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of any artificiall <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod,</hi> in that their holy courſe, whereinto they are entred towards <hi>Gods</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Which deſired and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for <hi>fruit,</hi> ſuch, I aſſure my ſelfe, ſhall, by Gods bleſsing, not faile to finde, that ſhall take paines, both
<pb facs="tcp:14796:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſeriouſly to acquaint them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with the <hi>directions</hi> in <hi>generall,</hi> and in <hi>ſpeciall</hi> tye themſelues to commit to memory thoſe mayne and <hi>Capitall</hi> places of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, laid downe, as it were the <hi>Text,</hi> in euery <hi>title,</hi> and by the <hi>letter</hi> differenced fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the reſt in euery <hi>ſection.</hi> Since theſe, in as much as they be the plaine words of <hi>Scripture,</hi> being once made their owne, will in ſuch ſort continually ſticke by them, and (more then any the things of men) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile with them; as that
<pb facs="tcp:14796:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> thereby they ſhall ſtill haue lodged within them, grounds of <hi>Pietie,</hi> and ſtore of <hi>knowledge,</hi> for their ſpirituall good, and daily growth in thoſe wayes of <hi>godlineſſe,</hi> which are the wayes to endleſſe <hi>happineſſe;</hi> which <hi>God</hi> graunt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>E. C.</signed>
            </closer>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 PET. 2.2.</bibl>
               <q>As new borne babes, deſire the ſincere milke of the word, that yee may grow thereby.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:14796:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A ſhort Table of the <hi>Titles</hi> and <hi>Texts</hi> of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall <hi>Letters</hi> of this <hi>Alphabet.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>A.</label> A <hi>Chriſtians charge, or ſumme of</hi> Religion. 1. <hi>Chro.</hi> 28.9. P. 1</item>
               <item>
                  <label>B.</label> The Sinners ſuite for dayly <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion.</hi> Pſalm. <hi>51. P. 3</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>C.</label> Dauids <hi>bleſſed man, or way to</hi> Life. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 1.1, 2. P. 7</item>
               <item>
                  <label>D.</label> The Doctrine and vſe of the Lords Supper. <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>11.23, 24</hi> &amp;c. <hi>P. 9</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:14796:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <item>
                  <label>E.</label> 
                  <hi>The forme &amp; force of</hi> Faſting. <hi>Ioel</hi> 2.12, 13, 14. Pag. 15</item>
               <item>
                  <label>F.</label> 
                  <hi>Diſcouery of ſinne by the</hi> Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.4. P. 22</item>
               <item>
                  <label>G.</label> The Practiſe and power of true <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</hi> Prou. <hi>28.13, 14. P. 25</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>H.</label> 
                  <hi>The Tenor of the</hi> New Couenant. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 36.25, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> P. 27</item>
               <item>
                  <label>I</label> 
                  <hi>The Leſſon of</hi> Sauing Grace. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11, 12, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> P. 30</item>
               <item>
                  <label>K.</label> The workes of the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and fruits of the <hi>Spirit.</hi> Gall. <hi>5.19,</hi> &amp;c, &amp; <hi>22.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>P. 32</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>L.</label> 
                  <hi>The Ladder of</hi> Bleſſedneſſe <hi>or</hi> 8. Beatitudes. <hi>Math.</hi> 5.3, 4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> P. 34</item>
               <item>
                  <label>M.</label> The ſtraitneſſe of the Gate &amp; Way
<pb facs="tcp:14796:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> to <hi>Life.</hi> Luke <hi>13.23, 24. Pag. 37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>N.</label> The Name of <hi>GOD</hi> proclaimed. Exod. <hi>34.6, 7. P. 39</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>O.</label> The power and efficacie of the Word Pſal. <hi>119.9,</hi> &amp; <hi>11. P. 43</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>P.</label> Reading the Word a meanes of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe. Reuel. <hi>1.3. P. 50</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Q.</label> Hearing of the Word another meanes Iam. <hi>1.21, 22. P. 54</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>R.</label> The continual Chriſtian watch, or eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry-daies Sabbath. Pſal. <hi>90.12. P. 56</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>S.</label> The Religious obſeruation of the Lords day, or Chriſtian Sabbath. Iſay <hi>58.13, 14. P. 63</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>T.</label> The Eſsentiall properties of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Charity. <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>13.4, 5, 6, 7. P. 67</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:14796:8"/>
               <item>
                  <label>V.</label> Direction for diſcharge of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar callings. <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>7.20,</hi> &amp; <hi>24. P. 69</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>W.</label> The Chriſtian care required for nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Youth. Prou. <hi>22.6. P. 74</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>X.</label> An <hi>Item</hi> againſt the exceſſe and abuſe of ſports. Prou. <hi>21.17. P. 77</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Y.</label> A Caueat againſt Drunkennes and exceſſe in drinking. Luke <hi>21.34. P. 80</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Z.</label> The difference of rewards for well-doing and ill. Jſai. <hi>3 10, 11. P. 85</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>&amp;. or &amp;c.</label> An Addition (for Concluſion) of ſome Rules for Knowledge, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripts, with formes of Prayer, <hi>P. 90</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14796:8"/>
            <head>An A. B. C. or holy <hi>Alphabet.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="A" type="part">
               <head>A.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> 
                  <hi>Chriſtians Charge</hi> contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and with a powerful <hi>reaſon</hi> preſſed, in <hi>Dauids counſell</hi> to <hi>Salomon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1 CHRON. 28.9.</p>
               <p>And thou <hi>Salomon</hi> my Sonne, know thou the God of thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſerue him with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect heart, and with a willing minde: For the Lord ſearcheth
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14796:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> all hearts, and vnderſtandeth the imaginations of the thoughts: if thou ſeeke him, hee will be found of thee; but if thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake him, hee will caſt thee off for euer.</p>
               <p>See places ſuteable hereunto, to force this <hi>Counſell</hi> farther.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.12.13. <hi>And now Iſrael, what doth the Lord thy God require of thee, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mica.</hi> 6.8. <hi>He hath ſhewed thee, O man, what is good, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eccles.</hi> 12.13.14. <hi>Let vs heare the concluſion of the whole matter, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All which, as they <hi>preſcribe</hi> what <hi>God</hi> expecteth, yeelding <hi>reaſon</hi> to moue vs to be thereof <hi>carefull,</hi> ſo do they alſo adminiſter both <hi>motiues</hi> and <hi>matter</hi> of <hi>prayer,</hi> to make vs earneſt with <hi>God,</hi> for his ſtrength and grace, to enable vs for a meete performance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="B" type="part">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:14796:9"/>
               <head>B.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>ſinners ſuite,</hi> or <hi>Dauids</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentant <hi>Prayer,</hi> after his <hi>fall,</hi> for <hi>himſelfe</hi> and the <hi>Church,</hi> not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to be vſed in our <hi>daily deuotion,</hi> in regard of our continuall failing in the precedent duties.</p>
               <p>PSAL. 51.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Haue mercy vpon me, O God, according to thy louing kindneſſe, according to the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of thy compaſſions, blot out my tranſgreſſions.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Waſh me throughly from mine iniquity, and cleanſe mee from my ſinne.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For I acknowledge my tranſgreſſions; and my ſinne is euer before me.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Againſt thee, thee only haue I
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14796:10"/> ſinned, and done euill in thy ſight: that thou mayeſt be iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, when thou ſpeakeſt, and be cleare when thou iudgeſt.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Behold, I was ſhapen in iniquity, and in ſinne did my mother conceiue me.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Behold, thou loueſt truth in the inward affections, and haſt made mee to know wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in the ſecret of my heart.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Purge me with<note n="a" place="margin">That is, with the bloud of Chriſt ſprinkled on my lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prous ſoule by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirit: <hi>Dauid</hi> for the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his faith, allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie in cleanſing the Leaper. <hi>Leuit</hi> 14.67. As ſee 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11.</note> Hyſope, and I ſhall be cleane; waſh me, and I ſhall be whiter then ſnow.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Make me to heare ioy and gladneſſe, that the bones which thou haſt broken may reioyce.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Hide thy face from my ſinnes, and blot out all mine iniquities.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Create in mee a cleane heart, O God, and renew a right ſpirit within me.</p>
               <p n="11">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:14796:10"/>11 Caſt mee not away from thy preſence, and take not thy holy ſpirit from me.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Reſtore to me the ioy of thy ſaluation, and ſtabliſh mee with thy free ſpirit.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Then will I teach tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſours thy wayes, and ſinners ſhall be conuerted vnto thee.</p>
               <p n="14">14. Deliuer me from<note n="b" place="margin">That is the guilt of bloud; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the particular ſinne that moſtwoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Dauids</hi> conſcience; as we, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this terme, may pray a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that particular ſin, which woundeth vs moſt, &amp; is to vs as bloud was to <hi>Dauid.</hi>
                  </note> bloud, O God, thou God of my ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and my tongue ſhall ſing aloude of thy righteouſnes.</p>
               <p n="15">15. O Lord open thou my lips, and my mouth ſhall ſhew forth thy praiſe.</p>
               <p n="16">16. For thou deſireſt no ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, elſe would I giue it thee, but thou delighteſt not in burnt offrings.</p>
               <p n="17">17. The ſacrifice of God, is a contrite ſpirit, a contrite and broken heart, O God, thou
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14796:11"/> wilt not deſpiſe.</p>
               <p n="18">18 Be fauorable for thy good pleaſure vnto <hi>Sion,</hi> build thou the walls of <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="19">19. Then ſhalt thou be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the ſacrifice of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, with<note n="c" place="margin">Theſe <hi>Dauid</hi> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneth, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe times; an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering whereto, are now the holy miniſtery of the word, the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, with pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, praiſes, &amp; thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing; As ſee <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14. 2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.15.</note> burnt offerings, and whole burnt offerings, then ſhall they offer young bullocks vpon thine Altar.</p>
               <p>And now to direct and encourage vs to this continuall duty of <hi>holy prayer</hi> (one moſt vſefull forme to furniſh vs, both for <hi>words</hi> and <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> whereunto may be, as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, this bleſſed <hi>Pſalme,</hi> to that end propoſed) take notice farther of theſe preſcripts, promiſes, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 7.7, 8. <hi>Aske, and it ſhall be giuen you, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.15. <hi>Call vpon mee in the day of trouble, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26.27. <hi>Likewiſe the ſpirit
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14796:11"/> alſo helpeth our infirmities, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jſai</hi> 65.24. <hi>Yea before they call I will anſwere, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.20.21. <hi>And while I was ſpeaking and praying, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 23. <hi>At the beginning of thy ſupplication the Commandement came forth, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All aſſuring vs of Gods readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, to <hi>heare,</hi> when euer by his grace he ſtirreth our hearts to <hi>pray,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee may euen <hi>propheſie</hi> of the ſucceſſe of our deſires: according to that acknowledgement, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.17. <hi>O Lord thou haſt heard the deſire of the humble, thou prepareſt their hearts, and</hi> (then) <hi>cauſeſt thine eare to heare.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="C" type="part">
               <head>C.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DAuids bleſſed man,</hi> pointing out yet more particularly the <hi>right path to life,</hi> in renouncing <hi>euill wayes,</hi> and cleauing vnto Gods <hi>word.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:14796:12"/>
               <p>PSAL. 1.1.2.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Bleſſed is the man, that walketh not in the counſell of the vngodly, nor ſtandeth in the way of ſinners, nor ſitteth in the ſeate of the ſcornfull.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But his delight is in the law of the Lord, and in his law doth he meditate day &amp; night.</p>
               <p>Agreeing hereunto, ſee likewiſe</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 22.21.22.23. <hi>Acquaint now thy ſelfe with God, and be at peace, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Epheſi.</hi> 5.8, 11. <hi>Yee were dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but now are light in the Lord; walke as children of the light. And haue no fellowſhip, &amp;c.</hi> As alſo <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.1.2.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 26.4.5.6.</p>
               <p>All warning vs, if euer we would be happy, aboue all to flye (as wee are ſtill in Scripture warned) the contagion of <hi>ill company,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.10.4.14.23.20.</note> that fixing our delight vpon Gods <hi>law,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14</note> we may entertaine familiarity and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14796:12"/> with the <hi>Lord,</hi> our both <hi>Sunne</hi> and <hi>ſhield;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.11 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16 11</note> in <hi>whoſe preſence is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ioy, and pleaſures at his right hand for euermore.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="D" type="part">
               <head>D.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>vſe</hi> of the <hi>holy Sacrament of the Lords Supper,</hi> (together with an adioyned <hi>directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> for a meete <hi>preparation</hi> thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to) deliuered by St. <hi>Paul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1. COR. 11.</p>
               <p n="23">23. For I haue receiued of the Lord, that which I alſo deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto you; that the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus in the ſame night that he was betrayed, tooke bread.</p>
               <p n="24">24. And when hee had giuen thankes, hee brake it, and ſaid, Take, eate, this is my body which is broken for you, this doe in remembrance of me.</p>
               <p n="25">
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:14796:13"/>25. After the ſame manner alſo he tooke the Cup when he had ſupped, ſaying, This Cup is the new Teſtament in my bloud; this do yee as often as yee drink it in remembrance of me.</p>
               <p n="26">26. For as often as ye eate this Bread, and drinke this Cup, ye doe ſhew the Lords death till he come.</p>
               <p n="27">27. Wherefore, whoſoeuer ſhall eate this Bread, and drinke this Cup of the Lord vnworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſhall be guilty of the Body and Bloud of the Lord.</p>
               <p n="28">28. But let a man examine himſelfe, and ſo let him eate of this Bread, &amp; drink of this Cup.</p>
               <p n="29">29. For hee that eateth and drinketh vnworthily, eateth and drinketh damnation <hi>(or iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment)</hi> to himſelfe, not diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Lords body.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:14796:13"/>
               <p>THe <hi>direction</hi> for <hi>preparation</hi> in the <hi>twelue queſtions</hi> following.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Queſt. <hi>How may a Chriſtian fit himſelfe for the Lords Table?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He muſt conſider
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>why</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>how</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list> he ſhold come thereunto.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Q. <hi>Why is he to come?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> In <hi>obedience</hi> to Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, who hath bidden vs ſo to doe, <hi>in remembrance</hi> of him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Q. <hi>What profit may hee expect hereby, to make him come willingly?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He is called by God to <hi>renew</hi> and <hi>confirme</hi> vnto his comfort, the <hi>couenant</hi> made betwixt <hi>Chriſt</hi> and him in <hi>Baptiſme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Q. <hi>What is that couenant?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That <hi>Chriſt</hi> will vndoubtedly <hi>ſaue</hi> vs, if wee with a liuely <hi>faith</hi> working by <hi>loue,</hi> ſhall <hi>cleaue</hi> vnto him.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Q. <hi>If there be ſuch gaine in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, what makes many ſo vnwilling to repaire often hereunto?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This is either for that being
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14796:14"/> groſly <hi>ignorant,</hi> they conceiue not rightly of the benefit: or elſe being carnall and <hi>careleſſe,</hi> they are loath to take paines to fit themſelues to come in that maner as <hi>Chriſt</hi> would haue them.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Q. <hi>To paſſe then to the ſecond conſideration, How would the Lord haue vs to come?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Not for <hi>faſhion</hi> or cuſtome (as it may be feared many doe) but in great <hi>reuerence,</hi> and with a due <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration,</hi> that wee may come <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Q. <hi>What</hi> preparation <hi>are we to vſe, that we may ſo come?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Euery one ought ſeriouſly to examine his owne ſoule, whether he can finde in himſelfe the <hi>graces</hi> by God required in worthy Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicants.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Q <hi>What be thoſe graces, which God chiefely requireth?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. A true <hi>faith</hi> grounded vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>knowledge</hi> of God and this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sacrament.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Sound <hi>repentance</hi> accompanied
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14796:14"/> with Chriſtian <hi>loue</hi> both to God and man.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Q. <hi>How ſhould a man examine or trie his faith?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> By well vnderſtanding the Articles of the <hi>Creede,</hi> with the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> ſet down by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. he may come to know what hee ſhould beleeue concerning God, and this holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament; which hee muſt labour to bring his heart vnto, and withall heartily begge of God (whoſe gift it is) to worke and encreaſe this true <hi>faith</hi> in him.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Q <hi>How is hee to trie his repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and charity?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> Labouring to finde out and bewaile his <hi>ſinnes paſt,</hi> and <hi>want of charity,</hi> with earneſt prayer to God for <hi>pardon</hi> and <hi>grace,</hi> he is to reſolue and purpoſe, to leaue off his ſinnes, and henceforth to liue in <hi>obedience</hi> to all Gods commandements, and in <hi>loue</hi> and <hi>charity</hi> with all men.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Q. <hi>Being thus prepared, how ought a Chriſtian to come vnto the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14796:15"/> LORDS Table?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> With great <hi>reuerence,</hi> and a feeling remembrance of the <hi>Lords death,</hi> for redeeming of his ſoule, he ought in all thankfulneſſe to <hi>reſigne</hi> and <hi>giue vp</hi> himſelfe wholly, and for euer vnto the <hi>Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. Q. <hi>After ſo communicating at Chriſts Table, what farther remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth by a Chriſtian to be performed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> His endeauour muſt bee to keepe ſtill in a ioyfull <hi>memorie,</hi> the <hi>promiſes</hi> ſo renewed, and by Chriſts blood <hi>ſealed,</hi> betwixt him and the Lord in the holy <hi>Sacrament,</hi> hereby to <hi>ſtrengthen</hi> himſelfe againſt ſinne, and to <hi>encreaſe</hi> faith and other gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in his ſoule, vntill God pleaſe to call him to the like againe.</p>
               <p>Adde here onely, how for <hi>triall</hi> of our <hi>faith</hi> required in the <hi>ninth Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion,</hi> as wee are to haue recourſe to the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Sacrament</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſet downe; ſo it will be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to young beginners, for the farther vnderſtanding of the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14796:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> Creede,</hi> to acquaint themſelues with the two other, namely, the <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene Creede</hi> beginning thus, <hi>I beleeue in one God, &amp;c.</hi> And that of <hi>Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius; Whoſoeuer will be ſaued, &amp;c.</hi> In which latter, the two great <hi>myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> of the <hi>bleſſed Trinitie,</hi> and our <hi>Sauiours</hi> holy <hi>Incarnation,</hi> are moſt excellently ſet forth and expreſſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="E" type="part">
               <head>E.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>forme</hi> and <hi>force</hi> of <hi>Religious faſting,</hi> together with a briefe <hi>Inſtruction,</hi> for farther explication, and Chriſtian practiſe.</p>
               <p>IOEL. 2.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Therefore alſo now, ſaith the Lord, Turne ye euen vnto mee with all your heart; and with faſting, and with weeping, and with mourning.</p>
               <p n="13">13. And rent your hearts and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14796:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> not your garments, and turne vnto the Lord your God: for hee is gracious and mercifull, ſlow to anger, and of great kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and repenteth him of the euill.</p>
               <p n="14">14. Who knoweth if hee will returne and repent, and leaue a bleſſing behinde him, euen a meate offering, and a drinke offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vnto the Lord our God?</p>
               <p>THe <hi>Inſtruction</hi> concerning <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting,</hi> deliuered alſo in Twelue ſhort Queſtions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Queſt. <hi>What doth the Scripture teach concerning Faſting?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Religious Faſting for furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Piety, is found commanded by God, and commended vnto vs by the frequent vſe of the beſt of Gods ſeruants in the holy Scriptures.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Q. <hi>What difference is there to be put betweene</hi> Prayer <hi>and</hi> Faſting?</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:14796:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Prayer</hi> is of daily and <hi>ordinary</hi> vſe, as the <hi>waſhing</hi> of plate or veſſell, continually to keepe them cleane: but <hi>Faſting</hi> is a thing leſſe <hi>ordinarie,</hi> and at times onely to be vnderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, as the <hi>ſcowring</hi> of ſuch plate or veſſell ſometimes, to make them bright.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Qu. <hi>When are Chriſtians enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to Faſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Goſpell hath not preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed any <hi>ſet dayes</hi> or times for this exerciſe, but then are Chriſtians to betake themſelues thereunto, when either they are enioyned by lawfull authority, or when God ſhall by the occaſions of extraordinarie <hi>humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation,</hi> as by his owne voyce, call and ſammon them ſo to doe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Qu. <hi>What</hi> occaſions <hi>be there of ſo</hi> humbling <hi>our ſelues</hi> before <hi>God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Either 1. When as for ſinne wee <hi>feare,</hi> or begin to <hi>feele</hi> Gods <hi>iudgements</hi> falling on vs: Or</p>
               <p n="2">2. When we deſire, or <hi>expect</hi> to receiue ſome <hi>ſpeciall</hi> and extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie <hi>good</hi> at the hands of God, as
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14796:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> when wee come to the holy <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> to renew our couenant with the <hi>Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Qu. <hi>Who are bound to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of this duty?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, if the <hi>Faſt</hi> for <hi>publique</hi> occaſions bee by authority enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, it concerneth <hi>all</hi> (except in caſe of neceſsity) to haue a due reſpect thereof.</p>
               <p>Secondly, for <hi>priuate Faſting,</hi> it ought to be by well-taught Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans vndertaken, as they haue war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant from the practiſe of the beſt of Gods holy ſeruants, ſtill vpon the like particular occaſions.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Qu. <hi>How are Chriſtians right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to performe this duty?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As in the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment touching the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> there are two things enioyned, 1. <hi>Reſt</hi> from labour, 2. <hi>Sanctifying</hi> of that Reſt; euen ſo, in this worke of <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting</hi> two things alſo are required:</p>
               <p n="1">1. The one <hi>outward</hi> reſpecting the <hi>body.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The other <hi>inward</hi> or ſpirituall,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14796:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> vnto which the <hi>outward</hi> is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Qu. <hi>What is the outward thing required in Faſting?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. <hi>Abſtinence</hi> from foode, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>altogether,</hi> or as farre as may be with preſeruation of <hi>health;</hi> as alſo from other <hi>delights,</hi> and outward comforts for <hi>humbling</hi> of the <hi>fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Reſt</hi> from labour, ſo far as with conueniencie wee may, during that time of <hi>abſtinence;</hi> that wee may the better intend the inward duty required in Faſting.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Queſt. <hi>What is the inward ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance chiefely required?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> An <hi>extraordinary humbling</hi> of our ſoule,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezr.</hi> 8.21.</note> and <hi>ſeeking</hi> after God by earneſt <hi>Prayer,</hi> and in the ſerious practiſe of true <hi>repentance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. Qu. <hi>How ſhould wee in the day of faſting exerciſe our ſelues in the ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous practiſe of true repentance?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> By diligent <hi>examination</hi> of our hearts and liues, by the rule of <hi>Gods</hi> Law, the <hi>ten Commandements,</hi> our labour muſt be, to get a thorow
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14796:18"/> 
                  <hi>ſight</hi> of our ſinnes, and ſinfull cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, diſpleaſing God, and deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing wrath: for which therefore we muſt deſire, and endeauour euen to <hi>rent our hearts,</hi> and to be truly <hi>humbled</hi> before the Lord with godly ſorrow.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Qu. <hi>How ſhall wee bring our hearts to this heart-renting ſorrow?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> The remembrance of Gods great <hi>kindneſſe,</hi> and our owne wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched <hi>vnthankefulneſſe,</hi> but eſpecially our <hi>looking</hi> vpon <hi>Ieſus Chriſt pierced</hi> for our ſinnes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10</note> and ſeriouſly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering what he endured to redeeme vs from death,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.10</note> are chiefe meanes to bring vs to this <hi>godly ſorrow, cauſing repentance not to be repented of.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. Qu. <hi>What may we expect vpon this humiliation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If being thus humbled in our ſelues, we ſhall <hi>repaire</hi> to God (and as in <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. <hi>EZra.</hi> 9. and <hi>Nehem.</hi> 9. we haue preſidents) ſhall <hi>penitently confeſſe</hi> our ſinnes with hearty <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> to God for <hi>pardon,</hi> and <hi>grace,</hi> and with a thorough reſolution, to <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14796:18"/> all our euill wayes,</hi> and hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth to <hi>liue in obedience</hi> to Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly will, we may haue aſſurance, that our ſinnes are pardoned, and ſhall finde grace renewed in our hearts, to make vs to performe what wee haue reſolued and promiſed.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Qu. <hi>How ſerueth the outward ceremonies of</hi> reſt <hi>and</hi> abſtinence, <hi>to this inward ſubſtance?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> The bodily exerciſe of <hi>Reſt</hi> and <hi>Abſtinence,</hi> is of profitable vſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In reſpect of <hi>time,</hi> which is thereby gayned for the better di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatch, without diſtraction of ſuch holy duties.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For the <hi>duties</hi> themſelues, whereunto theſe outward obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uances ſerue more or leſſe, either, as <hi>ſignes</hi> to teſtifie, or as <hi>helps</hi> to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our <hi>humiliation, prayer, and true repentance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Adde here, that for the better <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination</hi> of our hearts and liues (as is required in the <hi>ninth Queſtion:</hi>) it may bee fit for people, who are
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14796:19"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:14796:19"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:14796:20"/> more ignorant, to take a view of the explication made by M. <hi>Perkins,</hi> of the <hi>breaches</hi> of the ſeuerall Precepts, in his little Treatiſe of the <hi>nature and practiſe of repentance:</hi> as alſo it will be expedient for the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to obſerue, as <hi>keyes</hi> to open vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs the more full knowledge of the <hi>Commaundements,</hi> the <hi>Rules</hi> ſet downe in the ſection following.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="F" type="part">
               <head>F.</head>
               <p>SIxe generall <hi>Rules</hi> for the better vnderſtanding of the true <hi>mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> due <hi>extent,</hi> and binding <hi>power</hi> of the <hi>ten Commaundements,</hi> for the better diſcouering of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>ſinne,</hi> according to that ground of truth, and definition of <hi>ſinne,</hi> ſet downe by S. <hi>Iohn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1. IOHN 3.4.</p>
               <p>Whoſoeuer committeth ſin,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14796:20"/> tranſgreſſeth alſo the Law;<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>For Sinne is the tranſgreſsion of the Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>THE <hi>Rules</hi> are theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Where any<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.4 <hi>and</hi> 4.10.</note> 
                  <hi>duty</hi> is <hi>enioyned,</hi> the contrary <hi>ſinne</hi> is forbidden: and where any<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph</hi> 4.28 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4 3.4, 5.</note> 
                  <hi>ſinne</hi> is forbidden, the contrary <hi>duty</hi> is required.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Vnder one maine<note n="c" place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.15.</note> 
                  <hi>duty</hi> or <hi>crime,</hi> expreſly mentioned, all <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees</hi> and <hi>branches</hi> of the ſame kinde are either <hi>commaunded</hi> or <hi>forbidden;</hi> together with all<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro</hi> 23.31 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.22</note> 
                  <hi>occaſions</hi> or <hi>means</hi> furthering thereto, and all <hi>effects ſignes,</hi> or proper <hi>conſequents</hi> of the ſame.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Precepts</hi> being giuen <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally,</hi> doe <hi>binde</hi> all <hi>eſtates</hi> and <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> without exception,<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.19 <hi>Col.</hi> 3.25.</note> both <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues</hi> to keepe them; as alſo to take heede how they make themſelues<note n="f" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.11 <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.31.</note> 
                  <hi>acceſſaries</hi> to others breaking of them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. None can<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.12</note> 
                  <hi>diſpence</hi> with any
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14796:21"/> 
                  <hi>Commandement,</hi> but God onely; nor can any<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.2 <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.35 36.</note> 
                  <hi>breake</hi> them <hi>without ſinne,</hi> except by Gods <hi>ſpeciall warrant</hi> to the contrary; nor can any be held<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.10 <hi>Pſal</hi> 119.6. <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.21, 22.</note> 
                  <hi>conſcionably</hi> to obſerue <hi>any</hi> of them, that hath not a due <hi>reſpect</hi> to <hi>all</hi> of them.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The <hi>leaſt breach</hi> of any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, is<note n="k" place="margin">1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.4</note> 
                  <hi>ſinne,</hi> and in it ſelfe<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23</note> 
                  <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall,</hi> deſeruing euerlaſting wrath: yet in each Commandement are dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 5.22. <hi>Math.</hi> 7.2.</note> 
                  <hi>degrees</hi> of ſinne, and the breaches of the <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements</hi> of the<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.38. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.25</note> 
                  <hi>firſt table</hi> greater (comparing them in a <hi>lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> degree</hi>) then of the <hi>ſecond.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. One and the ſame <hi>duty</hi> or <hi>crime,</hi> may be in different reſpects referred to<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 25.18. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.5.</note> 
                  <hi>diuers Commandements,</hi> and the <hi>breach</hi> principally of <hi>one ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> be in other reſpects the breach alſo <hi>of the other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Scriptures</hi> cited in the <hi>mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent,</hi> being well conſidered, may giue ſome light for the iuſtifying and clearing of theſe <hi>Rules</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="G" type="part">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:14796:21"/>
               <head>G.</head>
               <p>THe knowledge of the <hi>Law</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a two-fold vſe, the <hi>one</hi> to <hi>humble</hi> vs by ſight of ſinne vnto <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,</hi> and the <hi>other</hi> to <hi>guide</hi> vs (being qualified by the <hi>Goſpell</hi>) in the way of <hi>righteouſneſſe;</hi> Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the practiſe and power of the former of theſe two, viz. <hi>repentance,</hi> wee may take it briefely in theſe words of <hi>Salomon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>PRO. 28.</p>
               <p n="13">13. He that hideth his ſinnes ſhall not proſper: but who ſo confeſſeth and forſaketh them, ſhall finde mercie.</p>
               <p n="14">14 Bleſſed is the man that feareth alwayes, but hee that hardeneth his heart, ſhall fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to euill.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:14796:22"/>
               <p>Agreeing whereunto, ſee thoſe <hi>counſels</hi> and <hi>comforts</hi> annexed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jſai.</hi> 55.6, 7, 8. <hi>Seeke ye the Lord whilſt, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.16.17, 18, 19. <hi>Waſh you, make you cleane, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As alſo that excellent place, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.10.11. where are ſet downe the <hi>ſeauen properties</hi> of true <hi>repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance:</hi> an expoſition whereof may be found in that plaine but profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and powerfull <hi>Sermon of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> made by M. <hi>Dent;</hi> which to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with his booke of the <hi>Plaine Mans Path-way,</hi> deſerue to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to ignorant perſons, and all yong beginners in the wayes of <hi>godlineſſe,</hi> to <hi>awaken</hi> them vp to ſome <hi>light</hi> and <hi>loue</hi> of <hi>life</hi> and <hi>ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="H" type="part">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:14796:22"/>
               <head>H.</head>
               <p>FOr further encouragement here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, let vs lay vp in our hearts the <hi>tenour</hi> of the <hi>new</hi> and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table <hi>couenant</hi> of <hi>grace,</hi> with the <hi>ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulation</hi> on our part by GOD re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired.</p>
               <p>EZEK. 36.</p>
               <p n="25">25. Then wil I ſprinkle cleane water vpon you, and yee ſhall be cleane, from all your filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; and from all your Idols will I cleanſe you.</p>
               <p n="26">26. A <hi>new</hi> heart alſo will I giue you, and a <hi>new</hi> ſpirit will I put within you, and I will take away the <hi>ſtonie</hi> heart out of your fleſh, and I will giue you a heart of <hi>fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="27">27. And I will put my ſpirit within you, and cauſe you to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14796:23"/> walke in my ſtatutes, and ye ſhall keepe my iudgements, and doe them.</p>
               <p n="28">28. And yee ſhall dwell in the land that I gaue vnto your Fathers, and ye ſhall be my people, and I will bee your GOD.</p>
               <p>After which followeth the <hi>ſtipu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> or condition on our parts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired.</p>
               <p n="31">31. Then ſhall ye remember your owne wicked wayes, and your doings that were not good: and ſhall loath your ſelues in your owne ſight for your iniquities, and for your abominations.</p>
               <p n="32">32. Be it knowne vnto you, that I doe not this for your ſakes (ſaith the Lord) there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be aſhamed and confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14796:23"/> for your owne wayes, O houſe of Iſrael.</p>
               <p>The ſumme of which ſaid coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, ſee alſo excellently expreſſed by the Prophet <hi>Ieremie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 31, 33, 34. <hi>Behold the dayes come (ſaith the Lord) that I will make a new couenant, &amp;c.</hi> And againe,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 32.38, 39, 40, 41. <hi>And they ſhall be my people, and I will be their God, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the effect, which is the ſtipu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation by God intended.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>EZech</hi> 16.62, 63. <hi>And I will eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh my couenant with them, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All to aſſure vs (that we may not doubt <hi>through vnbeliefe</hi>) of <hi>Gods thoughts of peace,</hi> &amp; his firme,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.20. <hi>Ier.</hi> 29.11.</note> as free <hi>purpoſe</hi> of good towards vs: hereby emboldening vs to importune, and euen implead the <hi>Lord</hi> vpon his promiſe, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſometime doth,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sa.</hi> 7.25.27. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.37</note> &amp; <hi>God</hi> expecteth his people ſhould, that ſo <hi>he may performe</hi> the ſame vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="I" type="part">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:14796:24"/>
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>ACcording to the tenour of this <hi>couenant</hi> of <hi>grace,</hi> and the other fore-named vſe of the right know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Law, is the <hi>leſſon</hi> of <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing grace,</hi> deliuered by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> to aduiſe <hi>ſeruants,</hi> and all of all ſorts to <hi>doe</hi> their <hi>duties,</hi> that they may <hi>adorne</hi> the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> and expect the <hi>glory</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> their <hi>Sauiour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>TITVS. 2.</p>
               <p n="11">11. For the grace of GOD that bringeth ſaluation hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to all men.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Teaching vs that denying vngodlineſſe, and worldly luſts, we ſhould liue ſoberly, &amp; righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly, and godly in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent world.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Looking for the bleſſed
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14796:24"/> hope, and the glorious appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the mighty God, and our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="14">14. Who gaue himſelfe for vs, that hee might redeeme vs from all iniquity, and purge vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to himſelfe a peculiar people, zealous of good workes.</p>
               <p>Anſwerable whereunto wee may take notice of thoſe <hi>Euangelicall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations,</hi> giuen by St <hi>Paul</hi> vpon the ſame ground, and to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1, 2. <hi>I beſeech you bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, by the mercifulnes of God, &amp;c.</hi> And 2. <hi>Cor,</hi> 7.1 <hi>Hauing therfore theſe promiſes, dearely beloued, &amp;c.</hi> And alſo that notable place (by lighting vpon which St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> confeſſeth himſelfe to be fully conuerted to the faith.<note place="margin">Lib 8 con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſ. cap. 12.</note>)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13 11.12, 13. <hi>The night is paſt, &amp;c. Therefore let vs walke as in the day, not in gluttony and drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14796:25"/> &amp;c. but putting on the Lord Jeſus, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All which agreeing with the <hi>rule</hi> of the <hi>new creature,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16.</note> promiſe <hi>peace,</hi> and <hi>mercie</hi> to as many as <hi>walke</hi> thereafter, and proue themſelues thereby, to be the true <hi>Iſrael of God, cleane-hearted,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.47.</note> and like <hi>Nathaniel,</hi> free from <hi>guile.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="K" type="part">
               <head>K.</head>
               <p>FVrther, for <hi>triall</hi> of our <hi>Chriſtian ſtate,</hi> and ſtanding in <hi>grace,</hi> that wee may know whether wee walke after the <hi>fleſh,</hi> or (as thoſe that are in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi>) after the <hi>ſpirit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1.</note> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue heedefully the <hi>workes of the fleſh,</hi> and <hi>fruites of the ſpirit,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, as contrary one to the other, by S. <hi>Paul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>GAL. 5.</p>
               <p n="19">19 Now the workes of the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14796:25"/> fleſh<note n="a" place="margin">That is, of that whole ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate, or of the fleſhly part of the man regenerate. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.18.</note> are manifeſt, which are theſe; adulterie, fornication, vncleaneneſſe, wantonneſſe,</p>
               <p n="20">20 Idolatrie, witchcraft, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, debate, emulations, wrath, ſtrife, ſeditions, hereſies,</p>
               <p n="21">21 Enuying, murthers, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, reuellings, and ſuch like: of the which I tell you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as I haue alſo told you in times paſt, that they which doe ſuch things, ſhall not inherit the Kingdome of God.</p>
               <p n="22">22 But the fruit of the Spirit<note n="b" place="margin">That is, of men made ſpiritual, or of the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall part in the man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate by Gods ſpirit.</note> is loue, ioy, peace, long ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, gentleneſſe, faith,</p>
               <p n="23">23 Meekeneſſe, temperance;<note n="c" place="margin">That is no law to hurt them, the curſe, which is the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of the law, being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away by Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13.</note> againſt ſuch there is no law.</p>
               <p n="24">24 And they that are Chriſts, haue crucified the fleſh with the affections and luſts.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:14796:26"/>
               <p>A like oppoſition whereto, wee may take notice of in other preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant places for the ſame purpoſe. As</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 3.5, 6, 7. <hi>Mortifie therefore your earthly memb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.15, 16 17, <hi>Loue not the world, neither the things of the world &amp;c.</hi> As alſo</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 3.15 <hi>In the</hi> difference <hi>put be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene</hi> earthly <hi>and</hi> heauenly wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, <hi>by the properties, and fruites.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All to learne vs true <hi>wiſedome</hi> to labour to finde our ſelues <hi>taught</hi> of <hi>God:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 54 13 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.11 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.14.</note> not caried by the world, or our owne <hi>luſts,</hi> but <hi>conſtrained by Chriſts loue,</hi> and <hi>led</hi> by his <hi>free ſpirit</hi> in the way to <hi>life.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="L" type="part">
               <head>L.</head>
               <p>MOreouer as ſure <hi>markes</hi> of our <hi>ſaluation,</hi> and <hi>earneſts</hi> in hand
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14796:26"/> of our future and full <hi>happineſſe,</hi> let vs ſtriue to climbe vp that <hi>Ladder of bleſſedneſſe,</hi> conſiſting of thoſe eight <hi>rounds,</hi> commonly called the <hi>eight beatitudes,</hi> deliuered by our Sauiour.</p>
               <p>MATH. 5.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Bleſſed are the poore in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, for theirs is the Kingdome of heauen.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Bleſſed are they that mourn, for they ſhall be comforted.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Bleſſed are the meeke, for they ſhall inherit the earth.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Bleſſed are they which hunger and thirſt after righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, for they ſhall bee filled.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Bleſſed are the mercifull, for they ſhall obtaine mercy.</p>
               <p n="8">8 Bleſſed are the pure in heart, for they ſhall ſee God.</p>
               <p n="9">9 Bleſſed are the peace-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, for they ſhall be called
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14796:27"/> the children of God.</p>
               <p n="10">10 Bleſſed are they which are perſecuted for righteouſnes ſake, for theirs is the Kingdome of heauen.</p>
               <p>Euidences of like nature on our part, to make ſure that our <hi>Election,</hi> the <hi>foundation</hi> whereof on <hi>Gods</hi> part <hi>ſtandeth firme</hi> and immoueable,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2, 19.</note> are thoſe eight linkes of St. <hi>Peters Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den chaine,</hi> to <hi>adorne</hi> themſelues wherewith <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are inuited.</p>
               <p>2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5, 6, 7, 8. <hi>Ioyne moreouer</hi> vertue <hi>with your</hi> faith, <hi>and with</hi> ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue knowledge, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>As alſo thoſe <hi>peculiar qualities</hi> of euery rightfull <hi>dweller</hi> in Gods <hi>Tabernacle</hi> and <hi>holy hill</hi> (by way of <hi>queſtion</hi> moued to <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>reſolution</hi> adioyned) <hi>deliuered by Dauid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.1. <hi>&amp;c. Lord who ſhall dwell in thy Tabernacle, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Selah</hi> or concluſion of <hi>aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:14796:27"/> in the <hi>Prophet</hi> and <hi>Apoſtle</hi> being the ſame, both to proue it <hi>at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineable,</hi> and to <hi>eſtabliſh</hi> the true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers heart therein (againſt <hi>all</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable doubting of falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from Grace) for <hi>who ſo doth</hi> (or) <hi>if ye doe theſe things,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.5. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10.</note> 
                  <hi>ye ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer fall.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="M" type="part">
               <head>M.</head>
               <p>FInally, to make vs yet the more carefull, that we be not ſhut out of Gods <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> let vs remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the <hi>ſtraitneſſe of the gate and way,</hi> and how for want of <hi>earneſt ſtriuing,</hi> many ſhall want deſired <hi>entrance,</hi> from that prying <hi>queſtion</hi> made to Chriſt, and that profitable <hi>reſolution</hi> thereupon by him deliuered.</p>
               <p>LVKE 13.</p>
               <p n="23">23 Then ſaid one vnto him, Lord, are there fewe that ſhall
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:14796:28"/> be ſaued? And hee ſaid vnto them,</p>
               <p n="24">24 Striue to enter in at the ſtraite g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te: for many I ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, will ſeeke to enter in, and ſhall not be able.</p>
               <p>A further explication and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation whereof, ſee, as in the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe publiſhed o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that<note n="*" place="margin">The ſtrait Gate and narrow way to life.</note> Text, ſo in the verſes following, 25, 26, 27. <hi>When the good man of the houſe is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen vp, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As likewiſe, <hi>Math</hi> 7 21, 22, 23. <hi>Not euery one that ſaith vnto mee Lord, Lord, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in that alſo, <hi>Math</hi> 5.20. <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept your righteouſneſſe exceede the righteouſneſſe of the Scribes, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All preſsing vpon vs, what is commended by our <hi>Sauiour</hi> in <hi>Iohn Baptiſts</hi> hearers:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.12.</note> and whereto both by St. <hi>Pauls</hi> example and exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we are directed, <hi>viZ.</hi> a <hi>follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.14</note>
                  <hi>hard towards the marke for the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14796:28"/> price of the high calling of GOD in Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1.</note> And <hi>running</hi> (therfore) <hi>with patience</hi> (in the footſteps of the faithfull gone before) <hi>the race that is ſet before vs looking</hi> that we faint not) <hi>vnto Ieſus</hi> himſ lfe,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ver.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>the Author and finiſher of our faith.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="N" type="part">
               <head>N.</head>
               <p>FArther, for a <hi>foundation</hi> of our liuel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>faith,</hi> and a <hi>furtherance</hi> of our godly <hi>feare,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.10.</note> that <hi>knowing Gods name, we may reſt thereon,</hi> and euer ſtand in <hi>awe</hi> of that <hi>glorious &amp; feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full name,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut</hi> 28.58.</note> THE LORD OVR GOD: Let vs take the <hi>ſame</hi> into our thoughts, as himſelfe hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed it before <hi>Moſes</hi> in mount <hi>Sinai.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>EXOD. 34.</p>
               <p n="6">6 The LORD,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> the LORD GOD, mercifull, and gracious,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14796:29"/> ſlowe to anger, and aboundant in goodnes and truth.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Keeping mercie for thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, forgiuing iniquity, and tranſgreſsion, and ſinne, and that will by no meanes cleare the guilty; viſiting the iniquity of the Fathers vpon the children vnto the third and fourth gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 18.10.</note>For this name, as the <hi>righteous running</hi> to it, haue ſtill found <hi>a ſtrong Tower</hi> to them of <hi>ſure defence;</hi> ſo may we likewiſe, if vpon all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons repairing thereto, wee ſhall for ſtrengthening of our <hi>confidence,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 20.6. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.24. <hi>Num.</hi> 14.17 2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 19.19.</note> to obtaine what we aske after the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of their faith, giue vnto God <hi>Titles ſuteable to our requeſts:</hi> hereby manifeſting, that wee relie not on any thing in our ſelues: but on the alone <hi>power, wiſedome, compaſsion, faithfulneſſe,</hi> and infinite <hi>goodneſſe,</hi> which are in <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to this end alſo how behooue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14796:29"/> will it be for the ſimpleſt <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,</hi> to learne and be well acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the meaning and ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the more ordinary <hi>names</hi> and <hi>titles,</hi> whereby our bleſſed <hi>Sauiour</hi> the <hi>Sonne</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> is in Scriptures ſet forth vnto vs, as (to omit all other) thoſe three eſpecially, of IESVS, IMMANVEL, &amp; CHRIST.</p>
               <p n="1">1. IESVS: an Hebrew name, ſignifying a <hi>Sauiour;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 7.45. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.11.</note> which though it bee found giuen in <hi>Type,</hi> and for ſome inferiour reſpects to <hi>others,</hi> is, in the full and perfect ſenſe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per onely to the <hi>Sonne</hi> of the bleſſed <hi>Virgine,</hi> ſent into the world to bee our IESVS, that is, our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> to <hi>ſaue vs his people from all our ſins;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 1.21</note> for <hi>neither is there ſaluation in any other;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 4.12.</note> 
                  <hi>there being among men none other name giuen vnder heauen, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we muſt be ſaued.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. IMMANVEL: an Hebrew compound name,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſai</hi> 7.14.</note> likewiſe giuen him of the <hi>Lord</hi> by the <hi>Prophet,</hi> and by
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:14796:30"/> the <hi>Euangeliſt</hi> interpreted, to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie as much as <hi>[God with vs]</hi> to note forth (for the Churches comfort) as the <hi>Vnion</hi> of both his <hi>natures</hi> in one <hi>perſon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.23. Nobiſcum Deus.</note> 
                  <hi>God with vs,</hi> that is, <hi>God made man</hi> by his holy <hi>incarnation:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.14. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5.</note> So alſo the <hi>effect</hi> and <hi>fruit</hi> of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, as <hi>mediator</hi> betwixt God and man, to make <hi>attonement</hi> and <hi>recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation</hi> for vs; for ſo hee was alſo our <hi>Immanuel, God with vs,</hi> that is, ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to reunite vs, who were fallen and ſeparated againe to <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>3. CHRIST, a Greeke name, anſwering to the H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>brew MES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIAS,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1 41. Vnctus.</note> both ſignifying the ſame, <hi>viz Annointed,</hi> to witneſſe him the <hi>annointed</hi> of the Lord, before pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, not in regard of any materiall oyle powred vpon him;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 9 21. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.2.</note> but for that hee was furniſhed with <hi>all fulneſſe of the holy Spirit,</hi> to be the onely and all-ſufficient, both <hi>Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh</hi> 1.16. <hi>Act.</hi> 11.26</note> and <hi>King</hi> of his Church; and of <hi>whoſe fulneſſe wee receiuing grace,</hi> are therefore called <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> as
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14796:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> partaking of that his <hi>annointing,</hi> and made thereby <hi>Prieſts and Kings to God his Father.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reu.</hi> 1.6.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Let the learned, if they light here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, beare with theſe plaine Explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which the ignorance of the common people (with griefe known to ſuch as haue any care o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Country charges) doth eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n ſeeme to enforce in theſe particulars.</p>
               <p>And thus farre (to adde no more) touching the <hi>name</hi> of <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="O" type="part">
               <head>O.</head>
               <p>FOr the <hi>power</hi> and <hi>efficacie</hi> of the word of God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 138, 2</note> whereby <hi>aboue all things, GOD magnifieth his name,</hi> Conſider that <hi>Quaere</hi> made and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued by <hi>Dauid,</hi> and his owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed <hi>practiſe</hi> ſuteable thereunto.</p>
               <p>PSAL. 119.</p>
               <p n="9">9 Wherewithall ſhal a young
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:14796:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> man cleanſe his way? by taking heede thereto, according to thy word.</p>
               <p n="11">11 I haue hid thy word in my heart, that I might not ſinne againſt thee.</p>
               <p>Where marke, hee ſaith not, <hi>J haue hanged it about my necke</hi> (as ſuperſtition of olde taught people, to doe the beginning of St. <hi>Iohns Goſpell,</hi> to driue away the deuill:) nor I haue <hi>had</hi> it in my <hi>houſe;</hi> or onely <hi>got</hi> it into my <hi>head;</hi> but <hi>hid it in my heart,</hi> viz. (by faith) <hi>that I might not ſinne againſt thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This being the commendations of the <hi>word</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> that it onely is able to <hi>cleanſe</hi> euen the <hi>young mans way,</hi> that is commonly moſt diſordered and diſſolute, in the <hi>pride</hi> of youth, and <hi>heate</hi> of luſt, and to preſerue from ſinne: yea, ſome word or other (ſo laid vp) from euery ſinne.</p>
               <p>As for ſome vſefull inſtances to confirme this truth.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:14796:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>1. From PRIDE <hi>(the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of ſinne)</hi> theſe places among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,<note place="margin">(<hi>Ecclus</hi> 10.13.</note> warning of the <hi>diſgrace</hi> and <hi>danger,</hi> or aduiſing to the contrary <hi>vertue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 11.2. <hi>When pride commeth, then commeth ſhame; but with the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is wiſedome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.6. <hi>God reſiſteth the proud, and giueth grace to the humble.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With that alſo of our Sauiour,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 11.29. <hi>Learne of me, for I am meeke, and lowly, and ye ſhall finde reſt vnto your ſoules.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From raſh SWEARING (that <hi>word cloathed about with death</hi>) the <hi>third</hi> great <hi>Commaundement</hi> (if it were as heedfully regarded,<note place="margin">(<hi>Ecclus</hi> 23.12.)</note> as it is often heard.)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.7. <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vaine, for the Lord will not hold him guiltleſſe, that taketh his name in vaine.</hi> And that counſell alſo agreeing thereto.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.12. <hi>Aboue all things my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren ſweare not, neither by heauen,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14796:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> nor by the earth, neither by any other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ath, but let your yea be yea, and your nay, nay, leſt yee fall into condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">(<hi>Ecclus</hi> 7.13.)</note>3. From LYING <hi>(the cuſtome whereof is not good)</hi> that fearefull place,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 22.15. <hi>Without ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll be dogs and Sorcerers, and murtherers, and Idolaters, and whoſoeuer loueth and maketh lyes;</hi> and where is that? but in the lake burning with fire and brimſtone; as ſee <hi>Reuel</hi> 21.8.</p>
               <p>And againe (which may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued a reaſon of the former ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence) that ſharpe cenſure giuen by our Sauiour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.44. <hi>Ye are of your Father the deuill, and the luſts of your Father ye will doe: he was a murtherer from the beginning, and abode not in the truth, becauſe there is no truth in him: when hee ſpeaketh a lye, hee ſpeaketh of his owne; for he is a lyer, and the Father thereof.</hi> And what Chriſtian would
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14796:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> be willingly accounted the childe of ſuch a Father?</p>
               <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">(<hi>Ecclus</hi> 31.30)</note> From DRVNKENNES (and <hi>Pot-good fellowſhip</hi>) which <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth</hi> ſo euery where <hi>the rage of fooles,</hi> That</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 23.29, <hi>&amp;c. To whom is woe? to whom is ſorrow? to whom is ſtrife? to whom is murmuring? to whom are wounds without cauſe? to whom is redneſſe of the eyes, euen to them that tarie long at the wine, &amp;c.</hi> And ſo ſee on forward to the Chapters end, a ſha pe inu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctiue againſt <hi>Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> diſplaying the wretchedneſſe thereof, to make people that haue any grace in them to abhorre it. And before,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 19, 20, 21 <hi>O thou my Sonne, heare and be wiſe, and guideth ne heart in the way: Keepe not company with drunkards and gluttons; for the drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard and glutton ſhall come to pouerty, and drowſineſſe ſhall cloathe ſuch with ragges.</hi> Loe, <hi>beggerie</hi> the faireſt end of ſuch <hi>good fellowſhip:</hi> then what
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:14796:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> thrifty perſon, beleeuing this, would not tremble at it? Finally,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 5.11, 12 <hi>Woe to them that riſe vp early in the morning to follow ſtrong drinke, and continue vntill night, till the wine enflame them, &amp;c.</hi> And</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 22. <hi>Woe vnto them that are mighty to drinke, and to them that are ſtrong, to poure in ſtrong drinke.</hi> And where <hi>God</hi> proclaimeth a <hi>woe,</hi> who dare or can promiſe <hi>peace?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5 From WHOREDOME, <hi>fornication,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">(1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.18.)</note> and vncleanneſſe (that peculiar <hi>ſinne againſt ones owne body.</hi>)</p>
               <p>1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9, 10. <hi>Know ye not that the vnrighteous ſhall not inherit the Kingdome of God, be not deceiued, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fornicators, nor idolaters, nor adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, nor wantons, nor buggerers, nor theeues, nor couetous, nor drunkards, nor raylers, nor extortioners, ſhal inherit the Kingdome of God.</hi> And therefore</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 18. <hi>Flie fornication, &amp;c.</hi> For ſee the <hi>reaſons</hi> vrged there againſt throughout the Chapter.</p>
               <p>And yet againe,</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:14796:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.4. <hi>Marriage is hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable amongſt all, and the bed vndefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: but Whooremongers and Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teres God will iudge.</hi> And where and how? but by <hi>excluding</hi> them, namely, out of heauen, and giuing them their portion (without Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption) in the <hi>Lake which bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth with fire and Brimſtone, which is the ſecond Death:</hi> as in the places fore alledged againſt <hi>Lying, Reuel.</hi> 22.15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 21.8.</p>
               <p n="6">6 From COVETOVS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NES, as other Teſtimonies, ſo that ſet Treatiſe of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.9.10.11. For <hi>thoſe that will be rich, fall into tentations and ſnares,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Who make it their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to be rich.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And that Caueat of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, with the annexed confirmation <hi>Luke</hi> 12.15. <hi>Take heede and beware of Couetouſneſſe, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo againſt <hi>carking</hi> CARE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FVLNES, that full Sermon of our <hi>Sauiour, Math.</hi> 6.25 <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (to the end.) <hi>Take no thought, &amp;c.</hi> Where is ſhewed, how <hi>Needleſſe, Boote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, Faithleſſe,</hi> and <hi>Fruitleſſe,</hi> ſuch care is.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:14796:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Finally, againſt <hi>quickly taking</hi> OFFENCE at others euill words, that <hi>Item,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.21.22. <hi>Take no heede vnto all words that are ſpoken, leaſt thou heare thy ſeruant curſe thee.</hi> For,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oftentimes alſo thine owne heart knoweth, that thou thy ſelfe likewiſe haſt curſed others.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>generally,</hi> what reſtraint we find from theſe, may vpon farther ſearch be likewiſe found in the ſame <hi>WORD,</hi> from <hi>all</hi> other Sinnes whatſoeuer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="P" type="part">
               <head>P.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Meanes</hi> of entertaining this <hi>Word</hi> into our hearts, ſo to preſerue <hi>from ſinne,</hi> and to make vs <hi>happy,</hi> is two fold, <hi>viz. Reading</hi> and <hi>Hearing,</hi> as</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:14796:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>REVEL. 1.3.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed is he that readeth, and they that heare, the words of Prophecie, and keepe the things that are written therein.</p>
               <p>Touching the <hi>firſt</hi> of which meanes, to wit, <hi>Reading,</hi> wherein by the <hi>Eye</hi> ſauing knowledge <hi>ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth</hi> into the <hi>Soule,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.18.19.</note> enioyned euen vnto <hi>Kings,</hi> amidſt all their moſt waightie affaires of State, we may receiue theſe directions.</p>
               <p n="1">1 That wee are to eſteeme it a great bleſſing of God, to bee able to <hi>read</hi> the <hi>Word;</hi> and thereupon labour to <hi>attaine</hi> it our ſelues, and to procure it as a ſpeciall <hi>portion</hi> to thoſe that belong vnto vs.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Hauing this ablilitie, Let vs follow the counſell of that good Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">In Coloſs. Homil. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>In getting into our hands this Booke of God,</hi> and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully making vſe thereof, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing in this libertie, which our
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:14796:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> Forefathers wanted; according to the wholeſome Praeſcript of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.39. <hi>Search the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, &amp;c.</hi> And the much honoured practiſe of thoſe Noble <hi>Beraeans, Acts</hi> 17.11.</p>
               <p n="3">3 In this exerciſe of <hi>Reading</hi> it will bee good to beginne betimes, and ſo to traine vp Children in this thriuing Trade,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim</hi> 1.5.</note> that (with <hi>Timothy,</hi> ſo well educated by his <hi>Mother</hi> and <hi>Grandmother</hi>) they may <hi>from their Childhood Knowe the Scriptures, which are able to make wiſe vnto Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, through Faith which is in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15.</p>
               <p n="4">4 To ſtirre vp People to this duty the better, Young beginners may be aduiſed ſeriouſly to read o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer once and againe, the 9. <hi>firſt Chapters</hi> of the Booke of <hi>Prouerbs,</hi> and euery day after, <hi>one Part</hi> of the 119. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> containing in <hi>ſumme</hi> a moſt excellent <hi>Meditation</hi> of the quickning <hi>power</hi> and <hi>profit</hi> of the <hi>Word,</hi> which <hi>Dauid</hi> out of the ſweet experience hee had himſelfe,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:14796:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> doth therefore ſeeke to commend to others.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Beſides this, (and the looking into the Scriptures vpon all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions for ſpeciall purpoſes,) it will be found profitable for Chriſtians to hold a conſtant courſe of <hi>Reading forward,</hi> in both Old and New <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament,</hi> ſo as their callings and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions ſhall permit, <hi>redeeming</hi> there to (with the noble <hi>Eunuche,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act</hi> 8.28.</note> who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen when he was trauelling, negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted not <hi>Reading</hi>) all good <hi>opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities;</hi> and when at any time they be caſt behinde by neceſſarie occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, recouering their loſſes by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubled diligence.</p>
               <p n="6">6 In this courſe of <hi>priuate Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> let people come with <hi>due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, deſire,</hi> and <hi>hope of profit,</hi> and <hi>looking vp to God for a bleſsing;</hi> wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly referring what they read to the right ends: with ſerious <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations</hi> and <hi>Prayers</hi> fitted to the things read; applying all for ſuch particular vſe as the Scriptures may affoord, and their eſtate require;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:14796:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> and ſtill in their reading, taking no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, (or ſome <hi>Note</hi> alſo, if they bee able for remembrance) of any thing wherein is occaſion of doubt, till they meet with an opportunity of inquiring reſolution.</p>
               <p>And ſo much for the <hi>rules</hi> of <hi>priuate Reading.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Q" type="part">
               <head>Q.</head>
               <p>FOr <hi>Hearing</hi> (the other outward meanes of receiuing the <hi>Word</hi>) eſpecially in the <hi>Publicke Miniſtry,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.17</note> the chiefe ordinary inſtrument of working <hi>Faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.2.</note> the Scripture it ſelfe giueth ſufficient direction: as</p>
               <p>IAMES 1.</p>
               <p n="21">21 Wherefore laying apart all filthineſſe, and ſuperfluity of naughtineſſe, receiue with meekeneſſe the Word to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graffed
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:14796:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> in you, which is able to ſaue your ſoules.</p>
               <p n="22">22 And bee yee doers of the Word, and not hearers onely, deceiuing your owne ſelues.</p>
               <p>Agreeing wherewith is that <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation</hi> alſo in 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 2.1.2. <hi>Wherefore laying aſide, &amp;c. As new borne Babes deſire, &amp;c.</hi> With many pregnant Teſtimonies, ſuch as that, <hi>Commendations</hi> giuen the <hi>Beraeans, Acts</hi> 17.11. <hi>Theſe were alſo more Noble men, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>thankes</hi> to God for the beleeuing <hi>Theſſaloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſs.</hi> 2.13. <hi>For this cauſe alſo thanke wee God, &amp;c. Cornelius</hi> his profeſsion of <hi>readineſs Acts</hi> 10.33. <hi>Now therefore are wee all here preſent before God, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes</hi> encouragement to <hi>attendance, Prou.</hi> 8.32.34. <hi>Heare inſtruction, and be wiſe, and refuſe it not: bleſſed is the man that heareth me, &amp;c.</hi> All ſeruing abundantly to ſtirre vp, and direct vs hereabout.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:14796:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>According to which <hi>grounds,</hi> there is a little Booke tranſlated into Engliſh, written by <hi>Zepperus,</hi> inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled the <hi>Art of hearing Sermons:</hi> which preſcribeth Rules both for praecedent <hi>Praeparation</hi> preſent <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention,</hi> and <hi>after vſe</hi> for profit, (as doe many other Treatiſes) ſo ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently, in this behalfe, that I need to adde no more; but onely counſel to take care, that our <hi>obedience</hi> of <hi>heart</hi> and <hi>life</hi> doe ſo continually fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low &amp; accompany this our <hi>hearing,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13.17 <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.25</note> that we may be bleſſed in our <hi>doing;</hi> and ſo build on the <hi>Rocke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 7.24</note> that wee may remayne vnmoueable in times of <hi>triall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this alſo touching <hi>Hearing.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="R" type="part">
               <head>R.</head>
               <p>THE commendations giuen<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.24</note> 
                  <hi>Henoch,</hi> and condition of the Couenant made with<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1</note> 
                  <hi>Abraham,</hi> in
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:14796:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Old Teſtament, and counſell for wiſe, and euen<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>preciſe</hi> walking with God, giuen by the<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Epeſ.</hi> 5.15</note> 
                  <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in the New; enforcing vpon vs a continuall wachfullneſſe ouer our hearts and wayes, doe neceſſarily bind vs to a prouident<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 16</note> 
                  <hi>Redeeming the time;</hi> and therefore to an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſeeking vnto God: which wee may be guided, vnto by that pithie <hi>Prayer,</hi> made to that very purpoſe by <hi>Moſes</hi> the <hi>man</hi> of <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>PSAL. 90.12.</p>
               <p>Teach vs (O Lord) ſo to number our dayes, that we may apply our hearts to wiſdome.</p>
               <p>According whereunto, that our Practiſe may be framed, theſe ſhort Rules may be obſerued.</p>
               <p n="1">1 For the time <hi>paſt,</hi> euery one ſo to come back to his own hart, ſaying,<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 8.6</note> 
                  <hi>What haue I done?</hi> As that it may abundantly <hi>ſuffice</hi> vs (as<note n="b" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.3</note> Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:14796:38" rendition="simple:additions"/> warneth) to haue <hi>miſpent the time paſt,</hi> according to the <hi>luſts</hi> of ſenſual men,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 2.</note> and reſolue <hi>for the ſpace re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining,</hi> wholly to conforme our heart and wayes vnto the <hi>Will</hi> of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2 For the time to <hi>come,</hi> ſo wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly euery one to conſider our <hi>latter ende,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deu.</hi> 32.29</note> forecaſting the vncertaine ſhortneſſe of our life, <hi>a <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>apour quickly vaniſhing,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iam</hi> 4.14.</note> and the ſtricktnes of our account, when euer we ſhall be called hence to <hi>Iudgement,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11</note> that we neuer ſing to our ſoules the rich mans <hi>Requiem, Luke</hi> 12.19. but rather with the <hi>Fiue</hi> wiſe Virgins, <hi>Math.</hi> 25.4. continually nouriſh in our ſelues, a <hi>watchfull</hi> expectation of the Bridgroomes comming.</p>
               <p n="3">3 For the time <hi>preſent,</hi> ſo euery one of vs, with all diligence to <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue</hi> our opportunities,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.16.</note> and <hi>employ</hi> our Talents, as that we may <hi>doe the worke of him that hath called vs</hi> in that day which he giueth vs,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9.4.</note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by preuenting our Sauiours <hi>teares,</hi> and making proofe, both to our
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:14796:38" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſelues and others, that we are taught to <hi>know in this our day,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 19, 41 42.</note> 
                  <hi>thoſe things that belong vnto our peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now for a familiar helpe vnto this heauenly skill, eſpecially to thoſe of younger yeares, whoſe hearts God ſhall touch,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.1</note> to <hi>remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber their Creator in the dayes of youth,</hi> and to endeauour with that noble Courtier <hi>Obadiah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 18.3, 12.</note> by <hi>fearing God timely,</hi> to feare him <hi>greatly;</hi> Let me adde, to aduiſe as a profitable courſe (if hauing skill to write, they be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled thereunto) the keeping of a <hi>Diarie</hi> or <hi>Journall,</hi> a booke I meane of daily <hi>remembrance</hi> for ſpirituall reckonings, ſuch as are their owne <hi>failings</hi> in duty towards God, need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing humbling; and <hi>Gods benefits,</hi> whether publique or perſonall, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring thankes. Which courſe, though I vrge not on all as neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; yet for them whoſe diſpoſition and leaſure ſuteth with it, and who ſhall be prouidently carefull onely of ſetting down matters of ſecrecie
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:14796:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> with ſuch abreuiations or chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters of their owne framing, as that themſelues onely may be priuie to them, it will be found (I doubt not) ſingularly profitable; as ſometimes it was to a young Noble-man of this Land,<note place="margin">The late Lord <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rington</hi> te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified in his Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Sermon made by M. <hi>R. S.</hi> and Printed <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 1614.</note> whoſe example and gaine thereby, may recommend it to all others, for daily obſeruation, and right ordering of their wayes, and eſpecially for weekely preparation to Sabbath-exerciſes, and furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelues principally for pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate extraordinary humiliations.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, to the end that our whole time may be better beſtowed, and we our ſelues againſt all oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions and impediments, may be at all times better armed: it ſhall not bee amiſſe to adnex for concluſion theſe <hi>two</hi> directions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For <hi>munition,</hi> to ſee we be euer armed with the <hi>Panoplie</hi> or <hi>compleat armour</hi> of a Chriſtian, deſcribed by St. <hi>Paul (Epheſ.</hi> 6,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 6 13.</note>) in the ſeuerall pieces; (but marke, no <hi>backe-piece,</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:14796:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> to learne vs, neuer to turne backe from our enemies) ſuch as are the <hi>girdle of truth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.7.</note> the <hi>breaſt-plate of righteouſneſſe</hi> the <hi>helmet of ſaluation,</hi> the <hi>ſhield of faith,</hi> and the reſt,<note place="margin">M. <hi>Gouge.</hi> M. <hi>Doun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham. Eph.</hi> 6.13.</note> which hauing beene by diuers largely ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto vs, I exhort onely with the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> that by <hi>feruent prayer</hi> they may bee daily buckled and girded vpon vs.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For <hi>meditation;</hi> concerning which, being the <hi>ſtudie</hi> (or ſerious muſing) <hi>of the minde,</hi> and ſo a chiefe furtherance either to good or euill actions, according to the obiects, whereon it is exerciſed, leauing the <hi>rules</hi> thereof to ſuch as haue exactly,<note place="margin">Doctor <hi>Hall.</hi>
                  </note> and at large diſcouered that <hi>Art</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs; I will onely adde, as generall heads, whereon profitably to ſet on worke our vacant thoughts in ſuch exerciſe, <hi>ſixe queſtions,</hi> all found in ſeuerall places of Scripture, in the very words wherein they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, <hi>viZ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:14796:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>1. What is man? [<hi>Pſa.</hi> 8.4.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ViZ.</hi> That hee ſhould be ſo highly aduanced.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Who am I? [2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.18.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ViZ.</hi> That I ſhould be ſo greatly regarded.</p>
               <p n="3">3. What haue I done? [<hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</hi> 8.6.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ViZ.</hi> For which I ſhould be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled.</p>
               <p n="4">4. What ſhall I doe? [<hi>Act.</hi> 16.30.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Viz</hi> That (yet) I may be ſaued.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Whither ſhall I flee? [<hi>Pſa.</hi> 139.7.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Viz.</hi> If ſinne be committed.</p>
               <p n="6">6. What ſhall I render? [<hi>Pſa.</hi> 116.12.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ViZ.</hi> For benefits receiued.</p>
               <p>And thus farre concerning the <hi>continuall</hi> Chriſtian watch, or <hi>euery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day-Sabbath,</hi> which they certainly obſerue beſt, who are carefulleſt to keepe the <hi>Lords day</hi> as they ſhould doe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="S" type="part">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:14796:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>S.</head>
               <p>TOuching the which <hi>Lords day,</hi> being to vs <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in place of the former ſeauenth day, or <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath,</hi> the ordinary <hi>Sabbath</hi> or weeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly day of <hi>holy reſt,</hi> founded on our <hi>Sauiours</hi> glorious <hi>reſurrection,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20.1. <hi>Act</hi> 20.7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.2</note> and from the <hi>Apoſtles practiſe</hi> (recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in holy Scripture) commended to the Church: I ſee not why wee may not, to raiſe vp our ſelues to the higheſt pitch of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deuotion therein, ſet before our eyes that religious and ſpirituall obſeruation of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto as one maine branch of <hi>piety,</hi> in thoſe times, put for the whole, the <hi>Iewes</hi> were inuited by promiſe of rich reward from God.</p>
               <p>ISAI. 58.</p>
               <p n="13">13 If thou turne away thy foot fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Sabbath <hi>(that is, as
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:14796:41" rendition="simple:additions"/> the words following ſhew, from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaning it, whereto by corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture all are carried)</hi> from doing thy will on my holy day: and ſhalt call the Sabbath a delight, the holy of the Lord honorable, and ſhalt honour him, not doing thine owne wayes, nor ſeeking thine owne pleaſure, nor ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thine owne words.</p>
               <p n="14">14 Then ſhalt thou delight thy ſelfe in the Lord, and I will cauſe thee to ride vpon the high places of the earth, and feede thee with the heritage of <hi>Iacob</hi> thy Father, for the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it.</p>
               <p>Some haue ſought to antiquate and quite aboliſh now vnder the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> the authority of the <hi>fourth Commaundement,</hi> as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in their Catechiſmes expunge the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond:</hi> And Athieſts and Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers would as gladly haue the <hi>firſt</hi>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:14796:41" rendition="simple:additions"/> and <hi>third</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>azed out. But both the <hi>deuotion</hi> and <hi>doctrine</hi> of <hi>our Church,</hi> ſtill directing vs to our <hi>ten Coman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>The ſame which God ſpake in Exod.</hi> 20. As ſee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n our Church <hi>Catechiſme</hi> and booke of <hi>Common Prayer,</hi> viz in the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> &amp; miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</hi>
                  </note>: and in particular to this<note n="*" place="margin">In the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of the time and place of Prayer.</note>: ſober minded <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ought, and will haue a due reſpect ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unto: and as we celebrate in ſteede of the <hi>paſſeouer</hi> the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> as the new S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>crament of the Goſpell, called for diſtinction from the former by St. <hi>Paul</hi> the<note n="a" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.20. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Lords Supper:</hi> So likewiſe, to obſerue in place of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> this <hi>firſt day</hi> of the weeke, as our Chriſtian <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and <hi>ſanctified day of reſt</hi> for holy worſhip, called, for like diſtinction by Saint <hi>Iohn</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Reu.</hi> 1.10. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> the <hi>Lords day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In which, as that bleſſed <hi>Apoſtle</hi> then in baniſhment was rauiſhed <hi>in the ſpirit,</hi> and ſaw heauenly viſions, and reuelations: So ſhould we alſo labour, <hi>who haue receiued the ſpirit,</hi> to be in what we may that day who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>ſpirituall</hi> and heauenly minded; ſo withdrawing our mindes and hearts, as farre as wee are able (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in caſes of more vrgent ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsities)
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:14796:42" rendition="simple:additions"/> from all <hi>diſtracting</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer <hi>buſineſſes</hi> or <hi>delights,</hi> as that wee <hi>deuote</hi> our ſelues, and be wholy taken vp in <hi>publique,</hi> &amp; more <hi>priuate</hi> ſeruices of <hi>Gods</hi> holy <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 92.1, 2</note> heau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nly <hi>contemplations,</hi> and workes of Chriſtian <hi>charity,</hi> as in an holy feſtiuall of <hi>reioycing</hi> before the <hi>Lord.</hi> Of which particulars ſo much hauing been written<note place="margin">In the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alledged of the time &amp; place of prayer: and in the <hi>Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, &amp;c. Exod.</hi> 20.8. <hi>Nehe.</hi> 13.22</note>, I ſpare to adde more, but onely exhort, that without either <hi>ſuperſtition</hi> or <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe,</hi> wee ſo <hi>remember</hi> before hand to prepare for it, &amp; euer when it commeth (as God would haue vs) to <hi>keepe</hi> it <hi>holy,</hi> that God may <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member vs in mercy,</hi> and we receiue the <hi>bleſsing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus alſo briefely for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of the <hi>Lords day,</hi> the more ſolemne Chriſtian <hi>Sabbath,</hi> or day of holy reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="T" type="part">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:14796:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>T.</head>
               <p>NExt, for direction touching <hi>Charitie,</hi> (that common and perpetuall <hi>Debt</hi> of Chriſtians,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 13 8 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1 22. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.10</note> 
                  <hi>owed</hi> generally to all, but with tender and <hi>brotherly</hi> affection to true <hi>Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers,</hi> profeſsing and giuing proofe of their <hi>precious Faith,</hi> and <hi>walking in Truth,</hi>) which St. <hi>Paul</hi> termeth the <hi>More excellent way,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.31. <hi>Col.</hi> 31 4 <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.10 <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13.34 <hi>Verſ.</hi> 35.</note> the <hi>Bond of perfectneſſe,</hi> and <hi>fulfilling of the Law,</hi> tying vs thereto by ſo many <hi>bondes;</hi> &amp; which our Sauiour himſelf ſtileth his <hi>New Commandement,</hi> &amp; maketh knowne, as the chiefe <hi>cognizance</hi> of his Diſciples: take notice of the <hi>fifteene</hi> properties hereof ſet downe.</p>
               <p>1 COR. 13.</p>
               <p n="4">4 CHARITIE <hi>(or Loue)</hi> ſuffereth long, and is kinde <hi>(or bountifull)</hi> Charity enuieth not,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:14796:43" rendition="simple:additions"/> charitie vaunteth not it ſelte <hi>(or is not thwarting,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>or doing fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly)</hi> it is not puffed vp.</p>
               <p n="5">5 It doth not behaue it ſelfe vnſeemely, it ſeeketh not her owne things: it is not eaſily prouoked, it thinketh none e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill.</p>
               <p n="6">6 It reioyceth not in iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but reioyceth in the truth:</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>7 It beareth <hi>(or couereth)</hi> all things, it beleeueth all things, it hopeth all things, it endureth all things.</p>
               <p>By which properties, the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning well apprehended, ſhall we try our hearts and liues (as we may doe alſo in the <hi>mutuall</hi> good <hi>offices</hi> of the <hi>bodily members,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.26.</note>) it may bee feared, we ſhall finde in vs much want of <hi>Charity;</hi> which ſince it argueth (by Saint <hi>Johns</hi> rule) weakeneſſe,<note place="margin">1 Ioh 4.20.</note> at leaſt in our loue to <hi>God,</hi> wee had the more neede to pray that <hi>God,</hi> who
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:14796:43" rendition="simple:additions"/> is <hi>Charity</hi> it ſelfe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ver.</hi> 16.</note> would by his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of <hi>loue</hi> beſtow vpon vs, and more and more heate and enflame in vs this quickning and working Grace.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="V" type="part">
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>FVrther yet, the exerciſe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of this grace of <hi>Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> being moſt obſeruable in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians carriage about their ſpeciall <hi>Callings;</hi> rules in Scripture are not wanting, (ſhall men conſult with theſe <hi>Counſellers</hi>) to guide Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in ſuch perſonall duties accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that generall <hi>charge,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.24.</note> as the maine and ſpeciall foundation laid by <hi>grace,</hi> of good <hi>order</hi> in humane ſocietie.</p>
               <p>1 COR. 7.20. &amp; 24.</p>
               <p>Let euery man, in the ſame vocation wherein hee is called,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> therein abide <hi>with God: (that
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:14796:44" rendition="simple:additions"/> is, doing duties to men therein, out of</hi> Conſcience <hi>towards God.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>More ſpeciall directions of which kind applyed to thoſe Domeſticall ſubordinations wherein <hi>Families</hi> are eſtabliſhed,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.21</note> that <hi>Each may ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to other in the feare of God,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his will, we ſhall find:</p>
               <p n="1">1 Of <hi>Husbands</hi> and <hi>Wiues:</hi> the ſumme whereof compriſed, <hi>Coloſs.</hi> 3.18.19. And more vnfolded, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſ.</hi> 5. and 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 3. conſiſting of <hi>feruent</hi> and <hi>faithfull loue</hi> in the <hi>Husband,</hi> and due <hi>ſubiection and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence</hi> in the <hi>Wife;</hi> is vſefully read, by order of our <hi>Church,</hi> in <hi>Marriage</hi> Solemnities, to make both parties (and their Neighbours alſo) more mindefull of their duties.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Of <hi>Parents</hi> and <hi>Children:</hi> the ſumme whereof grounded on the <hi>fifth Commandement,</hi> being in <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, Honour,</hi> and <hi>thankefull Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> to their <hi>Parents;</hi> In <hi>Parents,</hi> wiſe and due <hi>care</hi> for <hi>nurture,</hi> and <hi>education</hi> of their <hi>Children,</hi> and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:14796:44" rendition="simple:additions"/> way, towards them <hi>Loue,</hi> and <hi>ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der kindneſſe,</hi> is by the ſame Apoſtle alſo, both in <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3.20, 21, briefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly touched, and <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.1, 2, 3, 4. more fully opened, and by the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall <hi>Promiſe,</hi> annexed to the <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept,</hi> powerfully perſwaded.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Of <hi>Maſters</hi> and <hi>Seruants;</hi> the ſumme of the <hi>Maſters</hi> duty, which is, to doe that which is <hi>iuſt and equal to their Seruants, Knowing that they alſo haue a Maſter in heauen,</hi> that regardeth euery mans carriage, and <hi>reſpecteth no</hi> mans <hi>perſon,</hi> being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.9. and <hi>Coloſs.</hi> 4.1.</p>
               <p>But more expreſſely, and at large the duty of Seruants, (as needing in thoſe times moſt to bee remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred) ſet downe, as in other places, ſo in theſe following.</p>
               <p>COLOS. 3.</p>
               <p n="22">
                  <hi>22</hi> Seruants obey in all things your Maſters according to the fleſh: not with eye-ſeruice, as men-pleaſers,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:14796:45"/> but in ſingleneſſe of heart, fearing God.</p>
               <p n="23">
                  <hi>23</hi> And whatſoeuer ye doe, doe it heartily as to the Lord, and not vnto men.</p>
               <p n="24">
                  <hi>24</hi> Knowing that of the Lord yee ſhall receiue the reward of inheritance, for yee ſerue the Lord Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="25">
                  <hi>25</hi> But he that doth wrong ſhall receiue for the wrong that hee hath done, and there is no reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
               <p>TITVS 2.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <hi>9</hi> Exhort Seruants to bee obedient vnto their owne Maſters, and to pleaſe them well in all things, not anſwering againe.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <hi>10</hi> Not purloyning, but ſhewing al good fidelitie, that they may adorne the Doctrine of God our Sauiour in all things.</p>
               <p>1 PETER 2.</p>
               <p n="18">
                  <hi>18</hi> Seruants bee ſubiect to your
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:14796:45"/> Maſters with all feare, not onely to the good and gentle, but alſo to the fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
               <p n="19">
                  <hi>19</hi> For this is thanke worthy if a man for Conſcience toward God en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure griefe, ſuffering wrongfully.</p>
               <p n="20">
                  <hi>20</hi> For what glory is it, if when you be buffeted for your faults, ye ſhall take it patiently? but if when you doe well and ſuffer for it, yee take it pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, this is acceptable with God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All which places, ſufficiently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing the ſumme of</hi> Seruants <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, both to</hi> Maſters <hi>of all</hi> ſorts, <hi>and</hi> duties <hi>of all</hi> kindes, <hi>with the</hi> manner <hi>alſo of due performance, and the</hi> encouragement <hi>thereto; I haue thought fitting to haue ſet downe, to the end, that ſuch as want</hi> Bibles, <hi>or be not able to vſe them, may bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bee taught and minded of what belongeth to their places, &amp; be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged by thoſe gracious promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, which God hath made them, to beare that yoke which God hath layde vpon them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="W" type="part">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:14796:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>W.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Nurture</hi> and good <hi>Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of Childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; Youth, being the foundation of their weldoing, and their <hi>Parents,</hi> and others hopes, a weighty charge is layde on thoſe that take on them the care, <hi>diſcreet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> and <hi>betime,</hi> to <hi>teach</hi> and <hi>traine</hi> them vp in a right way, according to that <hi>Counſell</hi> giuen by <hi>Solomon,</hi> with the implyed reaſon.</p>
               <p>PROV. 22.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>6 Traine vp <hi>(or Catechiſt)</hi> a Childe in the trade of his way, and when he is old, he ſhall not depart from it.</p>
               <p>A ſpeciall part of which diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for towardly Educatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, being to be vſed (need ſo requiring, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of inbred and increaſing cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption)
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:14796:46" rendition="simple:additions"/> in ſeaſonable <hi>chaſtiſement,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ</hi> 6.4 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.29 1 <hi>Reg.</hi> 1.6.</note> that they may not for lacke thereof (as <hi>Elies</hi> ſonnes and <hi>Adoniiah</hi>) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an after griefe vnto their too indulgent Parents: wiſe <hi>Solomon</hi> hath giuen for that purpoſe theſe quickning directions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 13, 24. <hi>He that ſpareth his rod hateth his ſonne, but hee that loueth him, chaſteneth him betime.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 19.18. <hi>Chaſten thy ſonne while there is hope</hi> (implying that if hee once grow headſtrong, it will bee too late: witneſſe the complaint againſt an incorrigible child, <hi>Deu.</hi> 21.18) <hi>And let not thy ſoule ſpare for his crying.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">as <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> * <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.9. Shewing that cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement may be need full for ſuch as are riſing to yeares of ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The reaſon hereof ſee.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 22.15. <hi>Fooliſhneſſe is bound in the heart of a Childe</hi> (or* Youth) <hi>but the rod of correction ſhall driue it farre from him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Agreeing hereunto alſo is that,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 29.15. <hi>The rod and reproofe giue wiſedome, but a childe left to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe bringeth his mother to ſhame.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:14796:47"/>
               <p>And therefore finally that counſell againe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 23.13, 14. <hi>Withhold not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection from the childe</hi> (or<note n="*" place="margin">The word is ſtill the ſame as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</note> youth <hi>for if thou beateſt him with the rod, hee ſhall not dye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt beate him with the rod, and ſhalt deliuer his ſoule from Hell, viZ.</hi> by withdrawing him hereby from euill and ſinne, that would bring him vnto hell.</p>
               <p>All which places, expreſsing both the <hi>ground</hi> of ſuch <hi>chaſtiſement,</hi> which is the trueſt <hi>loue;</hi> and the <hi>ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, betimes,</hi> whiles there is yet <hi>hope,</hi> and the <hi>neceſsity</hi> implyed in the <hi>cauſe,</hi> and <hi>good conſequent</hi> thereof; (to omit others) I haue thought fit thus to ſet downe at large, as to make <hi>Parents</hi> and Gouernours mindfull of this tedious duty; ſo to this end chiefely, that <hi>children</hi> may ſo learne and marke them, as that <hi>correction</hi> being <hi>feared,</hi> may be the more <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented,</hi> or elſe, if at any time <hi>deſerued,</hi> and needfully <hi>inflicted,</hi> it may bee
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:14796:47"/> with more patience and profit <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="X" type="part">
               <head>X.</head>
               <p>TOuching <hi>Sports and Games,</hi> ſince they be of ſo frequent vſe, and the abuſe in theſe diſſolute times no leſſe common then the vſe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Scriptures ſpeake little in particular of them,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>See</hi> P. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr. loc. com. claſ. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> and therefore I ſhall ſay the leſſe; yet to adde ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to draw from the <hi>Exceſſe,</hi> and withhold from the <hi>Abuſe;</hi> let mee remember them that are thereunto addicted, of that one propheticall ſentence of the wiſeſt <hi>Solomon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>PRO. 21.</p>
               <p n="17">17 Hee that loueth Paſtime, <hi>(or ſport)</hi> ſhall be a poore man: and he that loueth wine &amp; oyle, ſhall not be rich.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:14796:48"/>
               <p>A true Prophecie oftentimes in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of outward penurie, experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence prouing how ſuch prodigall courſes bring <hi>the belly</hi> to <hi>huskes,</hi> and the <hi>backe</hi> to <hi>ragges,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 15.16 17. <hi>Pro.</hi> 23.21.</note> and the <hi>heart</hi> alſo, comming home to it ſelfe, to <hi>bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter teares.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But howſoeuer it fare with the outward ſtate, moſt certaine it is, that whiles ſuch (as if they were made onely to ſpend their time on the earth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 104.26 <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.5. <hi>Amos</hi> 6.3. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.7.</note> as the great <hi>Leuiathan</hi> in the Sea) ſo liue <hi>all in pleaſure,</hi> putting farre away <hi>the euill day,</hi> and (after the patterne of the Idolatrous Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites) <hi>ſit downe to eate and drinke, and riſe vp to play:</hi> they cannot chuſe but haue poore and beggarly ſoules, deuoid, if not of ſound knowledge, yet of true and ſanctifying grace, and thoſe fruits of grace, which ſhew themſelues in a well ordered life; theſe <hi>pleaſures</hi> being as <hi>thornes</hi> to choke the ſeed of the word,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk</hi> 8.14.</note> &amp; their ſurfetting thereupon, ſorting them within that corrupt confederacie,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1.4.</note> which make <hi>perilous</hi> the <hi>times,</hi> and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:14796:48"/> are branded with that deepe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued reproach,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> to be <hi>louers of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, more then louers of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Howbeit, in this, I denie not the vſe of all <hi>Recreations:</hi> ſome whereof are required by a true <hi>neceſsity;</hi> or yet of all <hi>Sports;</hi> ſome whereof may bee exerciſed lawfully for due de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, onely I would reſtraine the vſe of both, within the limits of the former <hi>leſſon</hi> of <hi>Grace:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11, 12.</note> which exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it ſelfe to all the paſſages of our whole life, and being aptly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to this particular, will ſerue to diſcouer, as by the negatiue branch of <hi>denying vngodlineſſe and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> worldly luſts,</hi> what rec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eations and ſports are allowed Chriſtians, <hi>viZ.</hi> ſuch as bee not <hi>vngodly</hi> in their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or the <hi>meere exerciſes</hi> of our worldly and ſenſuall luſts: ſo in the affirmatiue of <hi>liuing ſoberly, righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and godly in this preſent world.</hi> How theſe that be allowed may bee lawfully vſed, <hi>viZ. Soberly</hi> without <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> exceſſe for either affection or time, and <hi>iuſtly</hi> without either wrong or <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:14796:49"/> robberie to our ſelues or others, and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                  <hi>godly</hi> without either <hi>blaſpheming</hi> Gods <hi>name, prophaning</hi> his <hi>Sabbath,</hi> or <hi>hindering</hi> our ſelues and others from his ſacred ſeruice.</p>
               <p>All which inferre (mens conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences being witneſſe to them in this particular) a iuſt condemnation of this luxutious age, and may ſerue withall for the ſetling Chriſtians in a rightfull vſe of their Chriſtian li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty hereabout.</p>
               <p>And thus farre for the preſent, touching the abuſe and vſe of ſports.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="Y" type="part">
               <head>Y.</head>
               <p>TO touch briefely, ere we leaue, one other euill; (where vnder, in this laſt and luxurious age our Land <hi>groaneth;</hi> &amp; for which, amongſt other our many fearefull ſinnes, we may well feare the Lord is angry with vs) the idle and baſe humour of <hi>drunkenneſſe,</hi> and <hi>exceſsiue drinking,</hi>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:14796:49"/> if not alwayes to depriuation of ſenſe and reaſon, yet to diſtemper, and beyond the bounds of Chriſtian <hi>ſobriety,</hi> remaineth iuſtly to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued; our bleſſed Sauiour hauing giuen vs warning there againſt.</p>
               <p>LVKE 21.34.</p>
               <p>Take heede to your ſelues, leſt at any time your hearts bee oppreſſed with ſurfetting and Drunkenneſſe, and cares of this life, and leſt that day come on you at vnawares.</p>
               <p>For ſurely an <hi>Heatheniſh luſt</hi> this is, and <hi>worke of darkneſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.13. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.21. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20.</note> ill beſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſtians, yea a <hi>worke of the fleſh,</hi> and one chiefe point of that <hi>vnrighteouſneſſe, that excludeth</hi> quite from all portion of inheritance in <hi>Gods Kingdome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet how many of all conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may bee ſeene euery where, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully throwing themſelues into this Quagmire, or whirlepoole? which
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:14796:50"/> ſome haue likened to the <hi>pit of hell;</hi> out of which there is no redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> while ſome in a baſe loue of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                  <hi>loytring</hi> &amp; very idleneſſe, and others in an ouer-fond humour of ſhewing their good nature, or rather <hi>fooliſh <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> kindeneſſe,</hi> yea many in a <hi>vaine-glorious</hi> proud conceit and brauery, to proue their <hi>brutiſh valour,</hi> and withall wicked <hi>helliſh luſt,</hi> in aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turing <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> themſelues, to deforme <hi>Gods image</hi> in others,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.15.</note> and turne them into beaſts; all certainely for the want of <hi>grace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.1.</note> and the holy <hi>feare</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict themſelues ſo long to ſuch bib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing and bezelling courſes and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, till the wine and ſtrong drink, which <hi>Solomon</hi> termeth a <hi>mocker,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 20.1.</note> and <hi>raging,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.11.</note> depriueth them of their <hi>heart,</hi> and maketh them like <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadneZZar,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan</hi> 4.</note> brutiſh, and very ſots, and ſwine; ſo enſlaued to the pot, and giuen ouer vnto their luſt, that hardlieſt of all other offenders, and not without a ſtrong hand of grace, are ſuch reformed.</p>
               <p>This I heartily wiſh, that younger
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:14796:50"/> people, of themſelues inclineable (if Gods grace, or, at leaſt, good edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation ſtay them not) to ſuch rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous courſes, and who ſhall not want elder ones to draw them for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, would timely thinke vpon, and labour by <hi>Gods word ſtored in their hearts</hi> (as before they haue beene directed) and a continuall <hi>growth</hi> in ſound <hi>knowledge,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119 9</note> 
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.17.</note> and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying <hi>grace,</hi> to ſtrengthen them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 1 6.</note> that they be not caried away with ſuch <hi>error of the wicked.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for ſuch as, being hardned in euill wayes, regard not the terrours of Gods word, ſo they may ſatiate their ſenſuall luſts; howſoeuer they feare not either <hi>ragges</hi> and ruine to their ſtate,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 23.21. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 29.</note> or <hi>diſeaſes</hi> and deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties breeding in their bodies, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther finally dread the danger of Gods wrath and <hi>endleſſe deſtruction,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 24.49, 50.</note> ready (when <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall come, how ſoone they know not, and finde their <hi>hearts oppreſſed,</hi> and them <hi>vnprepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi>) to ſeaſe vpon their ſoules, and euerlaſtingly to torment both body
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:14796:51"/> and ſoule <hi>in hell,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal</hi> 9 16 <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.24</note> where they ſhall not finde ſo much as one <hi>drop of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> to coole their enflamed tongues.</p>
               <p>Yet oh, that ſome reſpect to their <hi>name</hi> and credit (which hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed with meere naturall men to reſtraine them from groſſer wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) might worke on them in this behalfe; ſo farre, at leaſt, that they leaue not their name to rot vpon the <hi>earth,</hi> as their bodies in the graue: that as <hi>Iudas</hi> is ſtill knowne by the name of <hi>Iudas</hi> the <hi>Traytour,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Act.</hi> 8.9.</note> and <hi>Simon Magus</hi> by the name of <hi>Simon the Sorcerer,</hi> ſo they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine not (to the ſhame of <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues</hi> and their <hi>poſterity</hi>) branded in the mouthes and memories of them that ſuruiue, with that reproach of <hi>ſuch an one,</hi> a very <hi>Swine,</hi> a <hi>Beaſt,</hi> a <hi>drunken companion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And let this ſuffice alſo for the preſent, for a checke to this <hi>beaſtly ſinne of the reaſonable creature,</hi> viz. <hi>drunkenneſſe</hi> and <hi>exceſsiue drinking.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Z" type="part">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:14796:51"/>
               <head>Z.</head>
               <p>ANd now, making ſtop for the preſent, from farther particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, that we may end with the iuſt number of our Letters, to preſſe to an heedfull regard of all deliuered; let mee beſeech vs all, to haue our eye fixed (with <hi>Moſes) on the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence of reward,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.26</note> yea on the <hi>diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> of <hi>rewards</hi> by <hi>God</hi> propoſed, according to that <hi>proclamation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>ISA. 3.</p>
               <p n="10">10 Say ye ſurely, it ſhall bee well with the righteous; for they ſhall eate the fruit of their doings.</p>
               <p n="11">11 But woe to the wicked, it ſhall be ill with him; for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of his hands ſhall be giuen him.</p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:14796:52"/>
               <p>A more full <hi>expreſsion</hi> of which <hi>ſumme,</hi> wee may reade in thoſe two notable Chapters of <hi>Bleſsings</hi> and <hi>Curſes, Leuit.</hi> 26.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Leuit.</hi> 26</note> and <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 28</note> And agreeing hereunto, ſhall wee finde the conſtant tenour of the <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Goſpell,</hi> which both turne vpon the ſame hinges.</p>
               <p>Onely with this maine difference; that the <hi>Law</hi> in it ſelfe conſidered, preſsing to the <hi>firſt</hi> couenant of <hi>workes,</hi> promiſeth the rewards of <hi>Bleſſedneſſe</hi> to the <hi>perſonall,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.5</note> 
                  <hi>full,</hi> and <hi>exact</hi> obſeruance, without admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring any the leaſt <hi>ſtrength</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the performance;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal</hi> 3.10 <hi>Deu.</hi> 27.26</note> withall threatning <hi>wrath,</hi> and the <hi>curſe</hi> for the leaſt failing or diſobedience.</p>
               <p>But in the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> which bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the latter Couenant <hi>eſtabliſhed on better promiſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb</hi> 7.19 <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.22</note> God offereth more <hi>Grace,</hi> and firſt accepting in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21</note> and for his alone righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe the <hi>perſon</hi> of the <hi>Beleeuer</hi> as truely <hi>iuſtified,</hi> and ſo perfectly righteous in his ſight; doth therby, ſo both take away the <hi>curſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13.</note> and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:14796:52"/> the <hi>rigor</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5.3 <hi>Pſa.</hi> 119.32</note> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſupply through the <hi>holy Spirit,</hi> a ſtrength of <hi>Grace</hi> to furniſh to the worke; That euen the <hi>Law</hi> it it ſelfe doth become to ſuch a <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect law of Libertie,</hi> and,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.25.2.12.</note> as it were a <hi>Goſpell:</hi> and both <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Goſpell</hi> ioine to promiſe, and aſſure a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and <hi>Crowne</hi> of <hi>righteouſneſſe:</hi> both for the preſent, and more fully hereafter, to <hi>ſincere,</hi> though <hi>weake</hi> and imperfect <hi>indeuour</hi> after <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs;</hi> according to the<note n="*" place="margin">Aliud eſt reddere ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum opera, &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liud redde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re propter opera, &amp;c. In Pſal. <hi>142</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>meaſure,</hi> though not for the <hi>merit,</hi> (as Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> well diſtinguiſheth) of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Chriſtians well doing.</p>
               <p>In which reſpect it is auouched concerning true <hi>Godlineſs,</hi> conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in the <hi>power,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5</note> and not the bare <hi>ſhape</hi> (or ſhadow) of Religion) though in the world ſo much deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that it is the <hi>greateſt gaine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.6 <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.8</note> onely able to giue <hi>content,</hi> and <hi>profitable to all things, hauing the promiſe of this preſent life, &amp; that that is to come.</hi> All to preſſe vpon vs the: <hi>Apoſtles</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, wherewith hee conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:14796:53"/> his ioyfull and tryumphant Doctrine, concerning the laſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.58</note> that namely, <hi>We ſhould be ſtedfaſt and vnmoueable, aboundant alwayes in the worke of the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">(<hi>Pr</hi> 23.18) (<hi>Heb.</hi> 6.17, 18.)</note> 
                  <hi>for as much as we know, (ſince ſurely there is an ende;</hi> Of which we neede not doubt, when God hath both by his <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Oath</hi> confirmed it) <hi>That our Labour is not in vaine in the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccls.</hi> 8.11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4 <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.15 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.21</note>On the contrary, for the <hi>wicked</hi> that preſume, becauſe God is <hi>Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,</hi> to goe on <hi>boldly</hi> in ſinfull cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and for that they are <hi>ſet vp,</hi> and <hi>proſper,</hi> Iudge <hi>God like themſelues,</hi> or, to like their doings well enough, hardning their fooliſh harts againſt the <hi>curſes</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.19</note> preſuming vp on the <hi>grace</hi> &amp; <hi>pardon</hi> of the <hi>Goſpell;</hi> how wretchedly doe ſuch deceiue themſelues, whiles the Lord for ſuch their preſumption hath perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily <hi>excluded</hi> them from all hope of <hi>mercy</hi> and the very <hi>Goſpell</hi> is turned,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>verſ.</hi> 20 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12 48 <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.16</note> as it were, into a <hi>Law,</hi> or <hi>Iudge,</hi> to paſſe ſentence on them for refuſing
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:14796:53"/> the offer of <hi>Grace</hi> therein made to them.</p>
               <p>Neither neede any other to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy their preſent proſperitie, who ſhal obſerue from thoſe <hi>two Pſalmes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. <hi>&amp;</hi> 73.</note> 
                  <hi>viZ. Pſal.</hi> 37. <hi>&amp;</hi> 73. to that very end compoſed, how their ſtanding is, though in <hi>high,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.13</note> yet in <hi>ſlippery places,</hi> (as that of the <hi>malefactor</hi> on the <hi>Ladder,</hi>) From which, if in this preſent Life, they be not with <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> tumbled; yet,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7</note> 
                  <hi>What is the hope of the Hypocrite, though he hath gayned,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob</hi> 27.8</note> 
                  <hi>when God taketh away his ſoule?</hi> And how will ſuch <hi>cry to the Mountaines and Rockes to hide them?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reu.</hi> 6.16.</note> when <hi>The Lord Ieſus ſhall ſhew himſelfe from heauen with his mighty Angels, in flaming fire,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.7, 3.</note> 
                  <hi>rendring vengeance to them that know not God, and that obey not the Goſpell of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>And thus farre touching the <hi>differences</hi> of <hi>rewards,</hi> and ſo for the <hi>Letters</hi> of this <hi>Alphabet.</hi>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:14796:54"/>
               <p>ONly as an &amp;. or &amp;c to cloſe vp all; let bee added for the benefit of the Simpler ſort (whoſe profit is here chiefly inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) a <hi>Rule</hi> or two to further <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> with ſome few <hi>Preſcripts</hi> and <hi>Formes,</hi> to <hi>ſet</hi> forward <hi>Deuotion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Rules</hi> of <hi>Knowldge</hi> ſhall be onely theſe two.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1 That Children bee from their <hi>tender Infancy,</hi> taught ſo ſoone as they can ſpeake the <hi>Language of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſai</hi> 19.18</note> and their tongues inured to the tearmes of <hi>Religion,</hi> euen before they be of capacity to vnderſtand the ſenſe or meaning, as being told, of <hi>God,</hi> and of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Heauen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">(<hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.2) (<hi>Mat.</hi> 12.01)</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and taught to anſwer, that <hi>God made them,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed them, &amp;c.</hi> and then made to
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:14796:54"/> learne the<note n="*" place="margin">As charge is giuen in the forme of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</note> words of the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> as alſo of the <hi>Creed,</hi> and <hi>Ten Commandements:</hi> The meaning whereof, and ſo of the whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>Catechiſme,</hi> may, as yeares in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and they grow capable, bee the <hi>ſooner</hi> by little and little inſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into them.</p>
               <p n="2">2 When ſuch, or any elſe (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> of riper yeares, who yet for want of better breeding, haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained as <hi>Children in vnderſtanding,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb</hi> 5.12 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.20</note> are once made perfect and groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in theſe principles, and parts of the common <hi>Catechiſme;</hi> for their better vnderſtanding thereof, it will be good for them, to be acqain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with ſome other more diſtinct directions, ſuch as is (among many others) that <hi>Guide vnto true bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Set forth by M. <hi>Sam. Crooke.</hi>
                  </note> or body of the doctrine of the Scripture, with the <hi>Abridgement;</hi> and eſpecially, as a moſt familiar and briefe <hi>ſumme</hi> of Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Maſter <hi>Perkins</hi> his <hi>Six prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples:</hi> wherein are compriſed ſo
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:14796:55"/> plainely and fully, the moſt neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full things for euery <hi>Chriſtian</hi> to know and beleeue, vnto ſaluation, concerning <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>our ſelues,</hi> our eſtate by <hi>nature</hi> without <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and of <hi>Grace,</hi> whereunto by <hi>Chriſt</hi> we are through <hi>Faith,</hi> wrought in vs by the meanes of <hi>Grace,</hi> recouered, and ſo conſequently our future e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of <hi>Glory;</hi> that I know no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or more compendious <hi>direction</hi> for any ignorant perſon, or of weake capacitie, whereby to try his ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall eſtate and ſtanding in <hi>Grace,</hi> then to referre him to thoſe 6. <hi>Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions,</hi> to ſee whether hee can finde himſelfe <hi>remoued</hi> out of that wrer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched <hi>condition,</hi> whereinto all are fallen, diſcouered in the <hi>Second,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that hopefull and happy eſtate, ſet forth in the <hi>Fourth</hi> principle; the ground wherof is layd in the <hi>third,</hi> the helping meanes in the <hi>fifth,</hi> and finally the <hi>fruite</hi> and accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment following in the <hi>laſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The right apprehenſion wherof, will make a Chriſtian fit, by ſo hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:14796:55"/> and <hi>reading</hi> the <hi>Word</hi> (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he hath bene directed) to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and <hi>grow in grace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet</hi> 3.18</note> 
                  <hi>and in the knowledge of our Lord and Sauiour Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this briefly for the <hi>Rules</hi> to further knowledge.</p>
               <p>FOr the matter of <hi>Deuotion,</hi> by which in this place, I meane a Chriſtians <hi>repayring</hi> dayly and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all occaſions vnto <hi>God,</hi> in hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble feruent <hi>Prayer,</hi> and hearty <hi>thankeſgiuing,</hi> according to thoſe <hi>Exhortions</hi> giuen by the <hi>Apoſtle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1 Theſſ. 5.17, 18. <hi>Pray continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ter, Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</note> 
                  <hi>In all things giue thanks: For this is the will of God in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Ieſus towards you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There may bee many <hi>Preſcripts</hi> giuen: but for direction ſtill, and helpe herein onely, of the more ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and weaker <hi>ſort;</hi> theſe fewe <hi>Aduertiſements</hi> ſhall for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſerue.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:14796:56"/>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1 For <hi>publike prayer,</hi> being the more ſolemne ſeruice of <hi>God,</hi> in the <hi>Chriſtian aſſemblies</hi> and congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>Church;</hi> let people make conſcience <hi>duly</hi> and <hi>timely</hi> to repaire thereunto (as the faithfull haue done) both on the <hi>Lords day</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 3.1 <hi>Luke</hi> 2.37 <hi>Leuit.</hi> 19 30.</note> as alſo in other <hi>Feſtiuals</hi> and <hi>times</hi> of <hi>prayer</hi> appointed by the <hi>Church,</hi> euermore <hi>taking heede vnto their feete</hi> (that is vnto the <hi>affections</hi> of the <hi>heart,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccle.</hi> 5.1</note> whereby they walke to <hi>God</hi>) when euer they come to <hi>meete</hi> the Lord in his <hi>houſe</hi> of <hi>prayer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.7</note> that they be <hi>neere to heare,</hi> and ſo ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in all meeke reuerence, and with pure affection, with the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter &amp; congregation in all the parts of Gods holy worſhip, that they ſuffer not <hi>drowſineſſe,</hi> or <hi>wandring thoughts,</hi> or <hi>talking</hi> with others, or <hi>reading</hi> in bookes (though of neuer ſo good vſe for priuate deuotion at other times) to withdraw their hearts from the buſineſſe in hand, making them to <hi>offer the ſacrifice of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:14796:56"/> fooles;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.13 <hi>Eccle.</hi> 5.4</note> in whom the <hi>wiſe God</hi> being of <hi>pure eyes,</hi> can haue no <hi>pleaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 For <hi>priuate deuotion,</hi> it concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> euery good <hi>Chriſtian</hi> of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer condition, man or woman, if not with <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Daniel</hi> thrice a day, yet, at leaſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.17 <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.10</note> 
                  <hi>morning</hi> &amp; <hi>euening</hi> ordinarily, to come before God on bended knees, as well taught chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, to <hi>aske bleſsing,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 6.11</note> and their <hi>daily bread</hi> of him <hi>our heauenly Father:</hi> and moreouer, <hi>often</hi> and <hi>ſtill</hi> vpon more ſpeciall occaſions in <hi>ſecret,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62.8</note> to <hi>poure out their ſoules to God,</hi> for ſuch graces and bleſsings as they ſtand in neede of; or to <hi>render humble thanks</hi> for his receiued fauours and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits.</p>
               <p>As helps to the weaker ſort, in which holy exerciſe (and perhaps neceſſary,<note place="margin">In M. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons</hi> helpe to Deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and The Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of Piety.</note> as <hi>Truckles</hi> are to young children, to learne them to goe) there want not many good &amp; whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome <hi>formes</hi> of <hi>prayers,</hi> already pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for ſeuerall purpoſes: But <hi>knowledge</hi> in the <hi>word,</hi> with a right
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:14796:57"/> vnderſtanding of the <hi>Lords prayer,</hi> and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. gotten into their heart; to ſuch as haue receiued of God the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10</note> will bee the beſt Schoolemaſter to <hi>helpe their infirmities:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26.</note> and to teach them how to make ſuites to God (no matter though in broken Engliſh, ſo it bee with contrite and broken hearts) according to the will of God: ſo as he the <hi>ſearcher</hi> of the hearts,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 27.</note> may know and graciouſly accept them in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3 Beſides theſe, there is one o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther duty of <hi>prayer,</hi> which concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth chiefely the <hi>gouernours</hi> of <hi>fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies,</hi> of whatſoeuer eſtate or condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who would haue the commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations giuen <hi>Cornelius,</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 10.2</note> 
                  <hi>of fearing God with all their houſholds,</hi> carefully to ſee performed in their <hi>families</hi> euery day, <hi>morning</hi> and <hi>euening:</hi> whereunto at times (as their occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions &amp; callings may permit) ſome<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.7</note> 
                  <hi>reading</hi> in the <hi>word,</hi> and<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>ſinging of Pſalmes,</hi> (with <hi>Catechiſing</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:14796:57"/> of their children and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 17.11.</note> repetition of what they haue heard, and ſuch like holy exerciſes) ſhould be profitably adioyned, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially on the <hi>Sabbath day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For this, as it will approue them<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19.</note> children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and men of<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 24.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> his godly reſolution, and make their houſes rightly accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as the faithfull ones by<note n="c" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16 19. <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 4.15</note> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaluted, as <hi>little Churches:</hi> ſo will it, not only free them from that <hi>execration</hi> made by the Prophet,<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ior.</hi> 10.25</note> againſt ſuch <hi>families as call not on Gods name,</hi> but giue them farther hope of <hi>Gods bleſsing</hi> (as ſometimes<note n="c" place="margin">2 <hi>Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 6.11</note> on <hi>Obed Edoms houſe</hi> for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Arke) vpon them and theirs, and<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob</hi> 5.24.</note> Gods peace to reſt and abide vpon their dwellings.</p>
               <p>Which religious duty of <hi>family-prayer</hi> (together with thankſgiuing, or Grace alwayes at our meales, by our <hi>Sauiours</hi> owne <hi>example,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.11. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5.</note> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> both <hi>preſcript</hi> and <hi>preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> recomme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to vs) howſoeuer, either through ignorance it bee in<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 27.35.</note>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:14796:58"/> many places vtterly vnknowne, or out of <hi>prophaneneſſe</hi> or <hi>want of ability</hi> for performance, it be wofully neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected in moſt families; yet being a <hi>ſeruice</hi> ſo well pleaſing vnto <hi>God,</hi> and of ſuch ſpeciall conſequence, I cannot but heartily wiſh, that it may be henceforward by all, that would be held to feare God, more conſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably practiſed, yea, euen among ſuch ignorant ones, and in ſuch ſmall poore families, where, through weakneſſe, and want of skill in any to reade, they bee able to doe no more then <hi>kneele down</hi> with their folke, and ioyne together in rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the <hi>Lords prayer,</hi> and praying God to bleſſe and keepe them: and (if they can get that alſo into their heads and hearts) making vſe of the 51. <hi>Pſal.</hi> before to that end propoſed, or of ſome other good forme of prayer,<note place="margin">The helpe to Deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of Piety.</note> ſuch as thoſe that are added in the end of our <hi>Bibles,</hi> and booke of <hi>Common Prayer:</hi> or which may bee found in other approued An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, or (if they want others) theſe
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:14796:58"/> 
                  <hi>ſhort formes;</hi> which for <hi>Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of theſe <hi>directions</hi> ſhall here bee <hi>annexed.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayers">
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A ſhort Morning Prayer for a Family.</head>
               <p>O Moſt holy and glorious <hi>Lord God,</hi> and in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> our moſt gracious and mercifull <hi>Father;</hi> as <hi>In thee we liue, mooue, and haue our being,</hi> and from <hi>thee</hi> doe dayly receiue our well-being, and all our <hi>good:</hi> So is it meet, and our boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den duty, by humble <hi>ſuit</hi> vnto thy <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> and hearty <hi>thankeſgiuing,</hi> to acknowledge and profeſſe the ſame vnto thy praiſe.</p>
               <p>Wee therefore thine vnworthy ſeruants, proſtrating our ſelues here before thy foote-ſtoole, doe render vnto thy <hi>Maieſtie</hi> all hearty <hi>thanks</hi> and praiſe, for all thy mercies and bleſſings continually beſtowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:14796:59"/> vs, both in regard of our ſoules and bodies, euer ſince we were born vntill this preſent: and in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar we bleſſe and praiſe thy <hi>Fatherly</hi> goodneſſe, for ſafe keeping vs this night paſt by thy watchfull proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, when wee could not keepe our ſelues; refreſhing vs comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with thy good bleſsing of ſleep, and raiſing vs vp againe in ſome meaſure of health and ſtrength this day to doe thee ſeruice.</p>
               <p>Now, O <hi>Lord,</hi> we beſeech thee, take vs into thy fauour, and <hi>Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> protection, and keepe vs conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually in thy moſt holy feare. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don graciouſly, and forgiue vnto vs, for <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> his ſake, all our ſinnes paſt: put them quite out of thy ſight, and purge them cleane out of our hearts; and ſo ſanctifie vs throughout with the grace of thy <hi>holy ſpirit,</hi> that we may take no longer delight to walke after the luſts of our owne wicked hearts; but may giue vp our ſelues hence-forward, wholly in obedience to thy
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:14796:59"/> bleſſed will, ſo doing, in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar this preſent day, the duties both of our generall &amp; ſpeciall callings, as that by thy bleſsing and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence being vpon vs, wee may be preſerued from all dangers that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe might befall vs, and finde much comfort in thy ſeruice: ſo as that at night wee may againe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, with reioycing and thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hearts, to reſigne, and giue vp our ſelues, both ſoules and bodies, into thine hands.</p>
               <p>Meanewhile, and euer, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber alſo, we moſt humbly beſeech thee, moſt mercifull <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> together with our ſelues, thy whole <hi>Church</hi> on earth, and all thine <hi>afflicted</hi> Children, and in particular this <hi>Land</hi> and Chriſtian Countrey wherein we liue: Herein bleſſe the <hi>Kings</hi> moſt <hi>Excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie,</hi> together with the <hi>Queene,</hi> and the <hi>Princes,</hi> the whole <hi>Royall</hi> Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, with the Nobles, and all ſet in Authority, and place of Charge or gouernment ouer vs, either in the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:14796:60"/> Church or Common-wealth: Our priuate Friends alſo, kindred and godly acquaintance, who are by any bond more neere vnto vs, or haue deſired to be in our prayers remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred by vs.</p>
               <p>In ſpeciall manner, bleſſe <hi>O Lord,</hi> this whole <hi>Family</hi> with all that belong thereto, or are therein; giuing vs all grace to liue in thy feare, and to doe thee ſeruice, ſo knowing our places, and endeauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with ſincerity and ſingleneſſe of heart to doe our duties, that wee may bee for comfort each to other, and all of vs in all things to thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, through <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> our bleſſed <hi>Lord</hi> and alone <hi>Sauiour:</hi> In whoſe holy Name wee continue to call on thee, and recommend our ſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, in that perfect prayer, which himſelfe did teach vs, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Our Father which art in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:14796:60"/>
               <head>A Grace, or bleſsing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Meate.</head>
               <p>GOod Lord, forgiue vs all our ſinnes, that make vs vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of any of thy bleſsings, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooue from vs all thy Iudgements which are vpon vs, or due vnto vs for the ſame: bleſſe and ſanctifie vs euer for thy ſeruice, and thy good creatures at this preſent for our vſe: giue them ſtrength to nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh vs, and giue vs grace for them, and all thy mercies, to bee thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to thee, and to receiue them as tokens of thy loue towards vs, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:14796:61"/>
               <head>A Thankeſgiuing, or Grace after meate.</head>
               <p>O Lord, wee giue thee humble thankes for all thy bleſsings beſtowed vpon vs, both for our ſoules and bodies, in regard of this life preſent, &amp; that to come; and in particular for refreſhing vs at this preſent with thy good creatures. We beſeech thee continue thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour vnto vs, and keepe vs euer in thy feare.</p>
               <p>Bleſſe thy whole Church, this Land, the King, Queene, and all the Royall Family: our friends, and all that are deare vnto vs. Grant thy Goſpell a free and a fruitfull paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage; comfort all thine aflicted ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, and guide vs in the right way to euerlaſting life, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:14796:61"/>
               <head>A Prayer for a Family in the Euening.</head>
               <p>O Lord God, gracious and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull, by whoſe watchfull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, wee thy poore and vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſeruants haue been this day pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, and with thy rich and vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued fauours, many wayes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted and bleſſed: wee returne to render vnto thine holy Maieſtie all humble and hearty thanks, for theſe and all thy benefits, and bleſsings, out of the euer-flowing fountaine of thy loue towards vs in Ieſus Chriſt, aboundantly powred downe vpon vs. O Lord, we doe confeſſe, wee be not worthy of the leaſt fauour, nay, hauing beene ſinners from the wombe, we deſerue wrath, and daily goe on to prouoke the eyes of thy Maieſtie to diſpleaſure, by our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold ſinnes and ſinfull corruption, ſtill vnto this day remaining in vs:
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:14796:62"/> and oft-times, euery day breaking out vpon vs to thy diſhonour.</p>
               <p>We acknowledge, O good Lord, our ignorance, and much want of deſire &amp; endeauour after the ſauing knowledge of thy bleſſed will, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed to vs in thy holy word: and wee haue iuſt cauſe to bewaile the prophaneneſſe and ſtubborne pride, and diſobedience of our hearts, which make vs daily to rebell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy moſt righteous lawes; both by leauing vndone the duties which thou enioyneſt, and aduentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vpon thoſe euill courſes, which thou forbiddeſt: yea, O Lord, our vile hypocriſie in our beſt ſeruices: our wretched vnthankfulneſſe for thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuall bleſsings: our murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring impatience vnder thy fatherly chaſtiſements and tryals: our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and abuſe of thy ſacred Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell: our blaſpheming of thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and fearefull name; and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaning of thy bleſſed Sabbaths: our ſelfe-loue and high-mindednes: our worldlineſſe and wicked coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe:
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:14796:62"/> our wantonneſſe, volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſneſſe, and other vncleane and ſinfull luſts: our wrathfulneſſe and maliciouſneſſe: our vnmercifulneſſe and impenitencie, and hard-hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tednes, and earthly mindednes, and a whole world of wickedneſſe; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the meanes of grace vouchſafed, ſtill abounding in vs: How doe they teſtifie againſt vs to our face, and in thy ſight, that wee are moſt wretched and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſinners, deſeruing in thy iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, (ſhouldſt thou enter into iudgement with vs) tenne thouſand deaths, and euen damnation in hell for euer.</p>
               <p>Howbeit, ſince we perceiue euen hereby, that it is of thine owne free goodneſſe, and gracious mercy, that we are not conſumed; becauſe thy compaſsions faile not, but are to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thine renewed euery mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and doe continue with them to the euening: We are emboldned to looke vp to thee, and in the name of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, in whom
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:14796:63"/> alone thou art well pleaſed, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee for his ſake to forgiue vs all our ſinnes, to waſh vs cleane in his bloud, and to aſſure our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence by the witneſſe of thine holy Spirit, of the full diſcharge, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of them all.</p>
               <p>Mercifull Father, wee moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly pray thee, for his ſake, to put them all, euery one of them, great and ſmall, out of thy ſight, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all by thy bleſſed Spirit, purge them more and more out of our hearts: O Lord giue vs grace euery day more and more our ſelues to ſee them, and the vileneſſe of them, and how baſe and filthy they make vs in thy ſight: and giue vs hearts to bee vnfainedly ſorrie, that wee haue by them offended thee our ſo gracious God, and grieued thine holy Spirit, whereby wee are ſealed to the day of redemption. Worke in vs an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and deteſtation of all ſinnes whatſoeuer, &amp; giue vs grace for the time to come, to ſtriue and labour againſt them (thoſe eſpecially wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:14796:63"/> we are by age, education, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, company, or any other oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion moſt enclined) as againſt the deadlieſt enemies of our ſoules.</p>
               <p>Yea, O Lord God, graunt that for this purpoſe wee may carefully ſhunne all occaſion of euill, ſuch as are idleneſſe, ill company, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe, wantonneſſe, and the like: and may more conſcionably entertaine and vſe all good meanes of grace, ſuch as are the hearing, reading, and meditating in thy holy Word, the often calling vpon thy holy name, the keeping of thy holy Sabaths, the receiuing of thy bleſſed Sacraments, the ioyning our ſelues in familiarity and fellowſhip with thy faithfull children, and the like; that by thy bleſsing hereupon, wee may encreaſe and grow together with our yeares and age, in faith, patience, and humility; in meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, temperance, and ſobriety, in loue vnto thee, and to thy truth, and to other for thy ſake; in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of this wretched world, which
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:14796:64"/> will ſhortly leaue vs, and a longing after the ioyes to bereuealed in thy Kingdome, and all good fruites of thy ſanctifying Spirit, which may fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther our reckoning, and ſeale vp our ſaluation vnto the day of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Meane while, wee continue our prayers, moſt mercifull God, for thy whole <hi>Church,</hi> and all the reſt of thy choſen children, who are our fellow heires of future glory, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they be ſcattered, eſpecially all thoſe who being in <hi>miſery,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in their ſoules or bodies, doe want thy more ſpeciall comfort. O Lord inſtruct them that yet are ignorant, conuert thoſe that are prophane, raiſe vp the fallen, ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then them that ſtand, and keepe vs that we neuer fall, but that our end may bee better then our beginning, and our workes better, and more at the laſt then at the firſt.</p>
               <p>Be gracious and good vnto all <hi>Chriſtian Churches</hi> that profeſſe thy Truth, reſtore peace (if it be thy
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:14796:64"/> bleſſed will) in thy good time to them which are troubled, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue peace and the light of thy Goſpell for euer vnto this, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in wee liue. Bleſſe herein wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee our <hi>Gracious King,</hi> and giue him an heart to feare thee, and ſeeke thy glory, to <hi>knowe thee, and ſerue thee, with a perfect heart, and a willing minde,</hi> that thou mayeſt bleſſe him, and his Throne for euer. Bleſſe alſo our <hi>gracious Queene,</hi> and giue her an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding heart to knowe the Truth, and with <hi>Mary</hi> to <hi>chuſe the better part,</hi> that ſhe may bee an hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per alſo and furtherer of thy glory. Bleſſe the reſt of the <hi>Royall Familie,</hi> the <hi>Counſell, Miniſtery,</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy</hi> in this whole Land, and all that haue place of command, charge or gouerment ouer others in the <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Common-wealth:</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, O Lord, bleſſe, we beſeech thee, all our <hi>Kindred</hi> and <hi>Friends,</hi> and ſpecially vs of this <hi>Family,</hi> that we may liue in thy feare, and bee
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:14796:65"/> bleſſed with all things neceſſary, both for our ſoules and for our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in this preſent life.</p>
               <p>And now, as thou haſt added this day vnto the dayes paſt of our life: <hi>Lord</hi> adde our repentance, wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, vnto the day; and let vs reſt in peace this night vnder the ſhaddow of thy winges, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing refreſhed by thy good bleſsing of ſleepe, which our beds cannot giue vs, but thou, O Lord, <hi>who giueſt thy beloued reſt,</hi> we may be inabled the better to ſerue thee in our cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, the day following, to thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, for others good, and our owne comfort, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, in whoſe name, we conclude our prayers as himſelfe hath taught vs, ſaying, <hi>Our Father, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:14796:65"/>
               <head>A priuate Prayer, framed (for the moſt part) out of the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Scriptures, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the <hi>51.</hi> Pſalme.</head>
               <p>O Lord God, mercifull and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, that forgiueſt iniquity, and yet <hi>wilt by no meanes cleare the guilty,</hi> I thine vnworthy and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Seruant, am bold to come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee, in confidence of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; but with all humble and free acknowledgement, that I am gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly guilty, and that by reaſon of the ſinne, both of my nature and life.</p>
               <p>For <hi>I was ſhapen in iniquitie, and in ſinne did my Mother conceiue mee.</hi> And this ſinne wherein I was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued (enough of it ſelfe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne me) hath bene too to fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in bringing foorth both ſinnes of Omiſsion, and Commiſsion in
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:14796:66"/> the whole courſe of my life, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it hath come to paſſe, that I haue neither denyed <hi>vngodlineſſe, and worldly luſtes; nor liued ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly, in this preſent world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I haue not <hi>knowne thee, my</hi> God, ſo much as I might, nor <hi>ſerued thee</hi> ſo well as I ought, but haue great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly failed euen in the moſt principall duties; not <hi>Reading</hi> thy Word ſo diligently; not <hi>hearing</hi> it ſo heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully; not receiuing the <hi>Sacrament</hi> ſo preparedly; not keeping the <hi>Sabbath</hi> ſo conſcionably; not <hi>cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vpon thy Name,</hi> ſo often and earneſtly as I ſhould haue done; much leſſe haue I regarded that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary ſeruice of <hi>Faſting</hi> and humiliation, though ſo many weightie occaſions, both publique and priuate, haue called vpon mee for it. And when I haue at any time performed theſe duties, it hath not beene with ſo <hi>perfect an heart,</hi> and ſo <hi>willing a minde</hi> as thou requireſt; but there hath bene
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:14796:66"/> much both <hi>heauineſſe</hi> and <hi>hypocriſie</hi> in my beſt Deuotions. I haue too to much diſtaſted and ſhunned <hi>the narrow way,</hi> not walking in my <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> ſo faithfully; not vſing <hi>Recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation</hi> ſo moderately, nor thy <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> ſo ſoberly, and inoffenſiuely; nor carrying my ſelfe towards my Neighbour (for the good both of his ſoule, and body, and ſtate) ſo religiouſly, <hi>Charitably</hi> and iuſtly, as it had beene meet I ſhould.</p>
               <p>But beſides this want of deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in thy Law and holy duties, I haue committed many grieuous ſinnes againſt thy Maieſtie, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very fearefully (eſpecially, in the time of You h and ignorance) both the <hi>Company,</hi> and the <hi>Counſels,</hi> and the <hi>Courſes</hi> of <hi>Wicked men,</hi> and ſo, inſtead of bringing forth the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and pleaſing <hi>fruites of the Spirit,</hi> haue wrought and brought foorth the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thy and noyſome workes of the <hi>Fleſh:</hi> Yea, O Lord, <hi>againſt thee, againſt thee haue I ſinned;</hi> and beſides Common euils, an guilty (as holy
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:14796:67"/> 
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> of bloud) of ſome notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſpeciall prouocations.</p>
               <p>Nor haue I beene thus ſinnefull, O Lord, for want of inſtruction and meanes to be better; for <hi>thou haſt taught me wiſdome,</hi> and made known thy <hi>Word</hi> vnto me, wherby I might haue bin <hi>cleanſed</hi> and amended; but it is becauſe I haue wanted care, &amp; haue not <hi>taken heede to my wayes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording vnto thy Word;</hi> nor <hi>laid vp that word of thine in my heart, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I might haue beene kept from ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning againſt thee:</hi> So that I can by no meanes iuſtifie my ſelfe; nay, O Lord, I am ſo farre from that, that ſay what thou wilt againſt mee in thy Word, lay what thou wilt vpon me with thy Hand, I doe freely confeſſe, <hi>Thou ſhalt be iuſtified when thou ſpeakeſt, and cleare when thou iudgeſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neuertheleſſe, O gracious Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſince thou haſt proclaimed thy ſelfe to be a <hi>God that pardoneſt ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, and tranſgreſsion, and ſinne;</hi>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:14796:67"/> Let me finde grace, I beſeech thee, in thy ſight, and <hi>pardon my ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, and my ſinne:</hi> I haue nothing to plead for my ſelfe, but <hi>Haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy on me, O God, according to thy lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing kindneſſe, according to the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of thy tender mercies, blot out my tranſgreſsions.</hi> I cannot deny, O Lord, but I am a great Sinner, but I know that the <hi>bloud of Ieſus Chriſt cleanſeth vs from all ſinne. Purge me</hi> therefore with that <hi>Hyſſop, and I ſhall be cleane, waſh me, and I ſhall be whiter then the Snow.</hi> So <hi>make me to heare the voyce of ioy and gladneſſe, that my heart</hi> (afflicted with ſinne) <hi>may reioyce in thee.</hi> Its true, O Lord, thou art a GOD that doeſt by no meanes <hi>cleare the guilty,</hi> yet, haue mercy on mee, while (by this meanes) the guilt of ſinne is remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from me.</p>
               <p>Nor doe thou onely <hi>Hide thy face from my ſinne, O Lord, and blot out all my iniquitie,</hi> but (together with the guilt of ſinne) take away the filthineſſe likewiſe: <hi>Waſh mee
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:14796:68"/> throughly from mine iniquitie, and cleanſe me from my ſinne;</hi> yea, <hi>Create in me a cleane heart, O God,</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new a right ſpirit within me:</hi> Vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe vnto mee the benefit of the new Couenant of grace, working that grace in me, that thou requireſt of me: <hi>Take away</hi> (more and more) <hi>the ſtony heart out of my fleſh and giue me an heart of fleſh;</hi> that ſo I may <hi>remember my former euill wayes, and my doings that were not good and loath my ſelfe in my owne ſight for my ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, and my abominations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Together with this <hi>Repentance</hi> (yea, that I may haue this Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance) worke in mee that <hi>Faith,</hi> whereby the <hi>Houſe of Iſrael enquires after thee;</hi> and whereby I a wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Sinner (finding my ſelfe <hi>heauy laden</hi>) may ſo come vnto thee as to haue eaſe from thee. And becauſe none ſhall haue <hi>mercy</hi> but hee that <hi>forſaketh his ſinne,</hi> as well as confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes it, Giue me ſo much grace as to <hi>forſake my wicked wayes,</hi> yea, and all <hi>my vnrighteous thoughts,</hi> that ſo thou
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:14796:68"/> mayeſt haue <hi>mercy</hi> on me, and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly pardon mee. And becauſe forſaking of ſinne is not enough, neither, without <hi>returning vnto thee</hi> my <hi>Lord</hi> and my <hi>God,</hi> make mee, I beſeech thee, to goe <hi>in the pathes of thy Commandements,</hi> and ſo <hi>put thy Spirit within me,</hi> as to <hi>cauſe mee to walke in thy Statutes, to keepe thy iudgements, and to doe them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus make me, by thy good gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, meet to receiue the benefit of thy gracious promiſes; And by that good grace of thine, doe thou (more and more) ſo enlighten mee, and ſo ſanctifie me, as that I may <hi>know thee the God of my Fathers,</hi> and <hi>ſerue thee with a perfect heart and a willing minde,</hi> and that both in the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of my <hi>generall</hi> and <hi>particular</hi> calling. Graunt that (for the time to come) I may <hi>reade</hi> thy <hi>Word,</hi> and marke it; that I may <hi>heare</hi> thy word and keepe it; that I may <hi>call</hi> vpon thy Name, and bee <hi>watchfull</hi> in it; that I may receiue thy <hi>Sacrament,</hi> and prepare for it; that I may keepe
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:14796:69"/> thy whole <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and delight in it; that when thou calleſt to <hi>Faſting,</hi> I may come to it willingly; and when thou requireſt the Sacrifice of <hi>Thanksgiuing,</hi> I may offer it freely. Graunt that, <hi>abſtaining</hi> as a <hi>Pilgrime</hi> and Stranger from <hi>fleſhly luſts,</hi> I may daily bring forth the <hi>fruites</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> ſtriuing mainely to enter in at the <hi>narrow gate,</hi> and, being in the number of thoſe <hi>violent</hi> ones, that take the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>heauen</hi> by <hi>force.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For which purpoſe, doe thou, O Lord, ſo preuaile with me, as that the power of Religion may be ſeene in all the paſſages of my <hi>particular</hi> calling: graunt that I may carrie my ſelfe faithfully in it, and vſe onely ſuch lawfull and moderate Recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as may bee helpfull vnto it, and thy creatures ſo temperately, as that I may not bee hindred, at any time, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> performing ſeruice to thee.</p>
               <p>Thus let mee obſerue the leſſon that Grace teacheth, carrying my ſelfe conſcionably towards thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, and iuſtly and charitably to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards my neighbour, and in my
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:14796:69"/> conuerſation ſo ſoberly, and with Chriſtian modeſty, that I may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the comfort that Grace promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, looking (with all aſſurance) for that bleſſed hope, and the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous appearing of the great God, and our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>In whom, being aſſured (while I endeauour to offer the Sacrifice of a <hi>contrite heart</hi>) that <hi>thou wilt not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe mee,</hi> I make bold (euen as my own ſins put me in mind, which help to make vp that heape of ſins which prouoke thee to puniſh thy whole Church) to entreate thy fauour in the behalfe of thy <hi>Church</hi> and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. <hi>Doe good in thy good pleaſure vnto Zion, and build thou the walls of Jeruſalem.</hi> Bee mercifull to thy Church in other parts; Make them carefull to bee holy, as thou their God art holy. Where thou haſt giuen proſperity, continue their comforts; where thou haſt ſent ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity, ſanctifie their croſſes; make them gracious by their ſufferings, and in thine owne good time glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:14796:70"/> by deliuerance.</p>
               <p>But in ſpeciall manner, I beſeech thee, be gracious vnto thy Church within theſe his Maieſties Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and in particular to this our Land. Aboue all things, continue the light, the purity, and the power of thy <hi>Goſpell</hi> amongſt vs, and giue vs grace to bring forth better fruit of it then we haue done, that it may not be <hi>taken</hi> away <hi>from vs,</hi> and <hi>giuen to another</hi> people.</p>
               <p>Herein amongſt, and aboue the reſt, let all thy bleſsings be powred downe vpon the head of our graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>King.</hi> Enrich him with all Princely gifts, and ſauing graces: <hi>Preſerue his life from deſtruction, and crowne him with louing kindneſſe and tender mercy.</hi> Bleſſe (together with him) his royall Conſort, and let the <hi>Queene be all glorious within.</hi> Bleſſe the <hi>Nobles</hi> with grace, together with their greatneſſe, that they may be powerfull inſtruments of thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and thy Peoples good. Bleſſe the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> of this Land, and
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:14796:70"/> make them zealous: All thy <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> likewiſe, and make them faithfull; that ſo by the power both of the word and ſword, wee may leade a quiet and a peaceable life in all godlineſſe and honeſty. Be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly good to all thoſe to whom I am any way tyed, either by the bond of nature, or grace, or loue, or duty. Sanctifie them by thy good Spirit, Proſper them by thy good prouidence, and graunt that they may firſt <hi>ſeeke thy Kingdome, that ſo other things may bee caſt vpon them.</hi> Be mercifull eſpecially vnto all that be afflicted in ſuch ſort, as that in the end euery one of thine may ſay; It is good for me that I haue beene afflicted, yea ſo, and ſo long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, O Lord, I deſire (as duty bindeth me) with all thankfulnes, to acknowledge thy manifold &amp; great fauours. Bleſſed (eſpecially) be God and the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, for ſpirituall bleſsings in heauenly things, and for giuing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:14796:71"/> ſuch vnworthy wretches as I am, Ieſus Chriſt, and together with him all things alſo; euen all thoſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward bleſsings: for which likewiſe (O gracious and mercifull Father) I deſire to bleſſe thy Name; to wit, for the bleſsing of health; the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of peace and liberty; the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of friends; that fatherly porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and fit allowance of outward things, which it hath pleaſed thee out of thy wiſedome and goodneſſe to allot vnto me, and for that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedneſſe, which together with it thou haſt beſtowed vpon mee. O Lord, I am leſſe then the leaſt of all thy mercies; yea, in ſtead of being thus bleſſed, I deſerue to bee euery way accurſed: But bee graciouſly pleaſed (Father of Mercies) to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue vnto mee theſe thy good bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, out of the ſame fauour of thine, whereby thou didſt at firſt ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd them; yea, and to adde vnto them likewiſe, what thou ſeeſt need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for me, that ſo enioying from thy good hand all proſperity and
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:14796:71"/> good content, my heart may be lift vp in thy wayes, ſo, as to performe vnto thee all cheerefull and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſeruice.</p>
               <p>Graunt this, O moſt mercifull Father, for Ieſus Chriſtes ſake, our alone Mediatour and Aduocate; vnto whom with thee, O Father, &amp; thy bleſſed Spirit, I humbly render, and aſcribe, and deſire to be giuen and aſcribed, all honour, praiſe, and glory, power, might, dominion, and Maieſtie, by mee, and thy whole Church, now, and henceforth, for euermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 119.130.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>The entrance into thy words ſheweth light, and giueth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding vnto the ſimple.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
